<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The power of Congregational churches asserted and vindicated in answer to a treatise of Mr. J. Paget intituled The defence of church-government exercised in classes and synods / by John Davenport.</title>
            <author>Davenport, John, 1597-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 229 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37205</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D362</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24876</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08630322</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08630322</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41503</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37205)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41503)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1255:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The power of Congregational churches asserted and vindicated in answer to a treatise of Mr. J. Paget intituled The defence of church-government exercised in classes and synods / by John Davenport.</title>
                  <author>Davenport, John, 1597-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 179 [i.e. 163] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Rich. Chiswell and to be sold by John Usher of Boston in New-England,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Paget, John, d. 1640. --  A defence of church-government.</term>
               <term>Congregational churches --  Government.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41503:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41503:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Power of <hi>Congregational Churches</hi> Aſſert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d and Vindicated, <hi>In Anſwer to a</hi> TREATISE OF Mr. <hi>J. PAGET,</hi> INTITULED <hi>The Defence of Church-Government exerciſed in Claſſes and Synods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> JOHN DAVENPORT; <hi>B.</hi> of <hi>D.</hi> and Paſtor to the Church in <hi>Newhaven</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 1.26.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I will reſtore thy Judges, as at the firſt, and thy Counſellors, as at the beginning: after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thou ſhalt be called, The City of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, the faithful City.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Rich. Chiſwell,</hi> and to be ſold by <hi>John <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> of <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> 1672.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:41503:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41503:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41503:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41503:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>TEe diſpoſals of GOD in his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with reference to the travels of Truth, and bringing forth of Light, are much to be obſerved, and have much to be read in them. There <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t been a great and over-ruling hand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted, and that very conſpicuouſly, about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preſent Treatiſe. The Reverend and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earned and eminently accompliſh'd Author <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rſt finiſhed a Tractate with this Title, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Subject, near thirty years ago: But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od's time was not yet come for its publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng: it periſhed therefore in the rude Waves of the vaſt Ocean, with ſome other excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent Manuſcripts and precious Chriſtians.
<pb facs="tcp:41503:4"/> Nevertheleſs, ſome ſeven years aft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, God ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him about it again, and then he finiſhed what is now (after twenty years more) thus made publick. Thus comes this ſhort an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nervous Treatiſe to have had a double, and ſo a more thorow digeſtion in the heart o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo judicious and holy a Servant of Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Nor are the principles and grounds her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> proceeded on ſuch as our Author ſuddenly or lately took up. He was of too ſerious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> weighty, and adviſed a ſpirit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lightly to take up, or ſuddenly to vent any ſingular apprehenſions in the things of God. It would be too long to relate, (though I could from his own hand) how he was firſt ſtaggered in his conformity, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards fully taken off by ſet Conferences and Debates, with himſelf and ſundry o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Miniſters obtained with Mr. <hi>John Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> then driven from <hi>Boſton</hi> on account of <hi>Nonconformity.</hi> Nor am I willin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> revive the Memory of what Afflictions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Author afterwards underwent, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> could not be ſatisfied in Conſcience in tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> two Points; <hi>viz.</hi> a particular Churches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubjected to a <hi>Claſſis,</hi> &amp; Baptizing in that latitude which was then practiſed, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtill in that Church, to which he had an earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Call, and with which the Lord gave him a very general and great acceptance. But
<pb facs="tcp:41503:4"/> certain it is, the Principles held forth in this Treatiſe, coſt the Reverend Author, not only many ſufferings, but alſo many, very many ſad ſearchings, and much reading, and ſtudy on ſet purpoſe, accompanied with manifold prayers and cryes to the Father of Lights for light therein. After all which he was more and more confirmed in them, and attained to ſuch comfortable clearneſs therein, as hore him up with much inward peace and ſatisfaction under all his afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the account of his perſwaſion in theſe Points. And ſo perſwaded, lived, and ſo died this grave and ſerious ſpirited man. The Reader will find in it (which is a rare conjunction) much ſuccinctneſs, with much Scripture clearneſs. Light contracted, like the Sun-beams in a Burning-glaſs, is the ſtronger, and would be the more grateful too, if it could poſſibly meet with an Eye able to receive it. There are that think, and as they conceive from Scripture grounds too, that the glory of the Saints in Heaven receives additions, and increaſes daily, as their holy walk, and faithful ſervice when here on Earth, doth after they are gone, bring forth Fruit to the praiſe of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe that are left behind them. If ſo, they that ever had any value and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for this Eminent Servant of Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:41503:5"/> (and there were, yea yet are many in whoſe hearts a precious remembrance of him lives, and will live for ever) are engaged to read and improve this Excellent Work of his for their inſtruction, and eſtabliſhment in the Truths of Chriſt. It was for ſeveral Moneths ſince ſent over from New-<hi>England,</hi> with deſire that it might be Printed. The wiſe and all-diſpoſing Providence of God allotted this as the ſeaſon for it, and in his ſeaſon all things have a peculiar beauty; and it may be preſumed that the hearts of God's p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ople are more generally prepared for a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy entertainment of light held out to them, and that the Lord will pleaſe to fulfil that good word of Promiſe upon all his faithful and humbled people, <hi>Ezek. 43.11. [And if they be aſhamed of all they have done,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
            <p>There are two things run through this whole diſcourſe, and are ligible even in every line of it.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> That the power of Churches is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to their <hi>Res Propria,</hi> their own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per matters.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That there is not any Spiritual Church-power, to which they are by any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Chriſt ſubjected. Two grand and Pillar-Principles of the Congregational-way, both of them abundantly cleared
<pb facs="tcp:41503:5"/> from miſtakes, and eſtabliſhed upon Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-foundations.</p>
            <p>Now the bleſſing of Heaven go with it, to lead the Reader into the truth of Chriſt in theſe Points, and to take off from the minds of ſuch of our Rulers, into whoſe hands this Book may fall, all thoſe prejudices a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Congregational-way, which it may have been unjuſtly miſ repreſented un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. For as in all the main matters of Faith and Doctrine we differ not from the eſtabliſhed publick Profeſſion of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, yea are much more tenacious thereof than many of our zealous adverſaries, ſo in thoſe things, which ſeem to be our moſt ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Opinions (and wherein we differ moſt from the publick Profeſſion, and for which we have ſuffered, and are ready by the grace of Chriſt ſtill to ſuffer even worſer matters, if the will of God be ſo concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us) this Book, after many others, which ſpeak the ſame Language, may ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it plain and evident to impartial and underſtanding Readers, the Principles and practices of the Congregational-way, are not in truth ſo incompatible with the power of the Supream Magiſtrate in matters of Religion, as ſome would repreſent, nor ſuch as may render them ſuſpected to Civil
<pb facs="tcp:41503:6"/> powers, and that therefore we may not for theſe our Principles be accounted unworthy to enjoy a peaceable dwelling in our native Land, the weal whereof is more dear to us than our lives, or all our private earthly enjoyments in it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. N.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>May 28. 1672.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="quotations">
            <div type="quotation">
               <pb facs="tcp:41503:6"/>
               <head>Tertull de praeſcr. adv. Haeret. Cap. <hi>21.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COnſtat omnem Doctrinam, quae cum Eccleſiis Apoſtolicis matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibus &amp; originalibus fidei conſpiret, veritati deputandam, id ſine dubio tenentem quod Eccleſia ab Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, Apoſtoli à Chriſto, Chriſtus à Deo ſuſcepit: reliquam veró om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inam de mendacio prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicandam, quae ſapiat contra ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem Eccleſiarum, &amp; Apoſtolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp; Chriſti, &amp; Dei.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="quotation">
               <head>Aug. de venit. Eccl. Cap. <hi>3.</hi> Tom. <hi>7.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Sunt certè libri Dominici, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb facs="tcp:41503:7"/> Authoritati utri<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſentimus, utri<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> credimus, utri<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſervimus: ibi quaeramus Eccleſiam, ibi diſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiamus cauſam noſtram.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="quotation">
               <head>Hieron. Epiſt. ad Minerium &amp; Alexandrum.</head>
               <p>Omnia probate, quod bonum eſt tenete—eſtote probati nummularij, ut ſi quis nummus adulter eſt, &amp; figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram Caeſaris non habet, nec ſignatus eſt moneta publica, reprobetur, qui autem Chriſti faciem claro praefert Iumine, in cordis noſtri marſupium recondatur.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41503:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Churches Charter. <hi>Containing Two Parts,</hi>
               </hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> The Conſtitution of particular viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Churches.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> The Priviledges and Power given to ſuch Churches.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <p>BEfore I proceed to examine Mr. <hi>Pagets</hi> arguing for the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Juridical Power of Claſſes, I ſhall poſitively declare what power is given by Chriſt to particular Churches, after I have deſcribed their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution according to Chriſt his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. In every of which particulars I ſhall principally inſiſt in the metaphor of a <hi>Corporation</hi> or body politick, ſuch as that of the chiefeſt and moſt perfect Cities is: becauſe I find, that it pleaſeth the Holy Ghoſt in Scripture, frequently to expreſs this matter under this ſimilitude.<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 48.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2. &amp; 87.3. Iſa. 26.1. &amp; 60.14. Ezek. 40.2. &amp; 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.35 Rev. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 21. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Luc. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> But I ſhall not venture to apply it any further than the light of Truth in Scripture will
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41503:8"/> direct and warrant: There we finde the grand Charter it ſelf, and the ancient Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents of the firſt Chriſtian Churches planted by the Apoſtles. According to theſe Records I ſhall endeavour to declare the mind of Chriſt, whom God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commands us to hear,<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 3.17 &amp; 17.5.</note> in all things whatſoever he ſaith unto us, and that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a dreadful penalty,<note n="†" place="margin">Acts 3.22, 23. Cypr. ad Coecil. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. ep. 3. Si ſolus Chriſtus audiendus eſt, non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendere quid ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis ante nos faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum putaverit, ſed quid, qui ante omnis eſt, Chriſtus prior fece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciendum ſtatuerit. Neque e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſequi oportet, ſed Dei veritatem, cùm per <hi>Iſaiam</hi> Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam Deus loquatur &amp; dicat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Whence Cyprian doth wel infer, <hi>If only Chriſt is to be heard, we ought not to attend what any before us thought ſhould be done, but what Chriſt, who is before all, hath done, and appointed to be done. For we ought not to follow the cuſtom of men, but the truth of God, ſeeing the Lord ſaith by the Prophet</hi> Iſaiah, <hi>In vain they worſhip me, teaching for doctrines the commandements of men.</hi> The Charter, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which particular Churches are to be conſtituted, and their power, <hi>in re propriâ,</hi> is to be ſtated; we find in <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18, 19. In the opening and explaining whereof, I purpoſe, with Chriſt's aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, to proceed in this method; 1ſt, hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the conſtitution of a particular viſible Church; 2ly, clearing the power of it.</p>
            <p>The words in <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18, hold forth a perfect Rule for the conſtituting of a viſible Church, of its cauſes, of which we ſhall ſpeak ſeverally, and diſtinctly; and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41503:8"/> the more largely, that the ſtrength of ſuch objections as occurr, in each particular, may be duly weighed; and in handling them, I ſhall obſerve this order.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall propound, what I conceive to be the truth, in certain doctrinal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions. 2. Explicate and confirm them. 3. Deduce thence ſuch Conſectaries or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences as freely flow from them.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe principal efficient cauſe is noted in this clauſe, <hi>I will build my Church.]</hi> I? who is that? even he, whom <hi>Peter</hi> had confeſſed in theſe words, <hi>Thou art the Chriſt, the Son of the living God.</hi> That is, Jeſus our Mediator. 1. He ſpeaks in the firſt Perſon, not in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: For though he uſeth men as his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, yet himſelf, by his Spirit, build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Church, <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.6. Therefore it is called, <hi>his Building,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9. 2. He ſpeaks not in the preter, or preſent tenſe, but in the future [I will build.] For though Chriſt was yeſterday, is to day, and ſhall be ever, the builder of his Church; yet he thus ſpeaketh in a particular reſpect to the Chriſtian Churches under the New-Teſtament,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41503:9"/> which ſhould be <hi>built</hi> (after his Aſcenſion) of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> joyned into one body, <hi>upon the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Prophets and Apoſtles, Jeſus Chriſt being the Corner-Stone, &amp;c.</hi> Epheſ. 2.20, 21, 22. The Concluſion hence is,</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>1</label> That Jeſus Chriſt our Mediatour is the only immediate Authour and Inſtitutor of particular viſible Churches.] That he ſpeaketh here of a particular viſible Church, and not of the Catholick Church, appeareth, by his giving to it the Keyes; Which, we ſhall prove hereafter, are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven only to particular Churches. 2. That Chriſt himſelf is the only immediate In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutor of ſuch Churches, may be evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; 1. Generally, from <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.3, 4, 5. 2. Particularly, by Induction, thus; 1. He is <hi>the Door, by whom</hi> they that are orderly admitted, muſt <hi>enter,</hi> Joh. 10.9. 2. He <hi>ſets the Members, every one of them,</hi> in that place and rank which they have <hi>in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.18. and gifteth them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.7. 3. He <hi>compacteth</hi> the whole Body, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.16. and firmly knits the materials together in this Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual building, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. 4. He gives the ſeveral Offices and Officers, Paſtors, Teachers, Ruling-Elders, and Deacons, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8, 11. 5. He ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointeth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41503:9"/> the viſible Seals, <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> Col. 2.10, 11, 12. and <hi>the Lords Supper,</hi> 1 Cor. 11, 23, &amp;c. 6. He is the Law-giver to his Church, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.12. 7. He is the Lord of all Church-<hi>Admininiſtrations,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.3. 8. The Cenſures have their power and efficacy from him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4, 5. 9. The bleſſing of all the Ordinances is from his Inſtitution of them, and effectual preſence with his Church and Miniſters diſpenſing them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19, 20.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
                  </label> Thus he is by a three-fold right. 1. From the Decree and Donation of the Father, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.7, 8. <hi>John</hi> 3.35. and 5.22, 23. 2. From the Redemption of his Church, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9, 10, 11. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18, 19, 20. 3. From his conqueſt over the powers of darkneſs, from whence he hath delivered them, and tranſlated them into his Kingdom, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13.</p>
               <p>In all theſe reſpects, and many more, Jeſus Chriſt, our Mediatour, hath right to inſtitute particular Chriſtian Churches, and to caſt them into what mould he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth.</p>
               <p>From this Concluſion, thus proved, I infer, as followeth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Conſect.</hi> Then Jeſus Chriſt is the only Lord, and Head of ſuch Churches as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41503:10"/> himſelf hath inſtituted. Thus from Chriſt's <hi>building his Houſe,</hi> followeth his <hi>being over the Houſe,</hi> Hebrews 3.3, 6. And he is over it, as the Lord of it, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.36. And as the only Political Head of it, in three reſpects, 1. Of Prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, as having the Spirit in a greater meaſure than all his Members, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.18. <hi>John</hi> 3.34. 2. In reſpect of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.22, 23, 24. 3. In reſpect of Influence, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.5. and that, not only in reſpect of common Gifts, whereof Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites partake, which, if they be joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Chriſt's viſible Body, the Church, are but dead Members, whom, as dead Branches in the Vine, God will take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and caſt forth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.2, 6. but alſo in reſect of quickning Grace, whence they are called, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. Hence they <hi>grow up in all things into him which is the Head, Chriſt;</hi> and are edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and edified Members in the Body, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.15, 16.</p>
               <p>Nor is Chriſt the Head only of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, but alſo of every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church inſtituted by him, which is therefore frequently by Chriſt himſelf cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>the Kingdom of God, and of Heaven,</hi> the King whereof is Chriſt; his Subjects are viſible Believers, profeſſing their Faith
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41503:10"/> in him, and their ſubjection to his Laws, and Ordinances, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13. This Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign power is ſo properly Chriſts, that it is not communicable to any Creature; nor can any man be his Subſtitute or Vicar herein. For neither doth Chriſt, or his Church need ſuch a Vicar, or viſible Head of the Church, ſeeing the Church is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat in Chriſt alone, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.10. Nor is any Creature capable of diſcharging the Office of an Head unto the Church, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.20, 21, 22, 23.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Conſect.</hi> Then it is not in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Earthly Kings or States, or Civil Courts, to make Eccleſiaſtical Laws, or to invent and impoſe any Rites or Forms of Worſhip upon Churches, according to Principles of State-Policy, or Humane Prudence. Though <hi>Moſes</hi> was, as well a great Prophet, as a great Prince, yet God left no part of the building of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle to his prudence, but limited him in all things to the pattern in the Mount, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.40. Nor might <hi>Solomon,</hi> though the wiſeſt of meer men, act by his own wiſdom in building the Temple,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Chon.</hi> 28.11, 12, 13.</note> but he was guided therein by the perfect pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, which <hi>David</hi> gave him from the Spirit. So concerning Chriſtian Churches, Chriſt hath given his People a perfect pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41503:11"/> which he requireth the Miniſters to hold forth diſtinctly in every point of it, to his people; according to that Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.10, 11. <hi>That they may keep the whole Form thereof, and all the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thereof, and do them;</hi> which alſo Chriſt expreſly requireth in <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19, 20.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Conſect.</hi> Then every particular vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church muſt exalt Chriſt and his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions alone, in their whole Church-Order, and in all their Admiſtrations. This is their viſible <hi>receiving Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, and walking in him,</hi> Col. 2.5, 6. The Church is Chriſt's Houſe; and it's e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual, according to Natural light, and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil prudence, that every man ſhould bear Rule in his own Houſe, <hi>Eſth.</hi> 1.22. Much more Chriſt, who is God and Man. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxerxes</hi> ſhall riſe up in judgment with all ſuch as incroach upon Chriſt's Right, in ordering Churches by their policies, and condemn them; for he, fearing the jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſy and wrath of God, if men ſhould take ſuch liberty to themſelves, provided againſt it, by a ſtrict Decree, ſaying, <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is commanded by the God of Heaven, let it be diligently done for the Houſe of the God of Heaven; for why ſhould there be wrath againſt the Realm?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Eſth.</hi> 7.23.</p>
               <p>Nor is the wrath of Chriſt leſs formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41503:11"/> to us, or his jealouſie leſs incenſed againſt thoſe, that, either add to, or take from, or alter his Inſtitutions now, than in times paſt; but rather more, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.25. to the end.</p>
               <p>So much ſhall ſerve touching the Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Cauſe and Inſtitutor of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular viſible Churches.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Concerning the Material Cauſe.</head>
               <p>THe Materials whereof this Spiritual Building muſt conſiſt, are implyed, when Chriſt ſaith, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Rock will I build,</hi> &amp;c. together with <hi>Peters</hi> confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in <hi>ver.</hi> 16. and Chriſt's approbation of it, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. which gave occaſion to this Speech of Chriſt, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Rock,</hi> &amp;c. For the Rock is Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. But how conſidered? not ſimply, and in an abſtract ſenſe; but, 1. As Preached by the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20. 2. As believed on with a Faith made vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible by publick confeſſion, according to <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.9, 10. Chriſt believed on, is the Foundation, or Rock, of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick inviſible Church: But Chriſt believed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41503:12"/> on and confeſſed, is the Rock whereupon a particular viſible Church is built. In this Expoſition, ſundry of the Ancient Writers,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Baſil. Tract. de poenit. Gre. Naz. de Comp. <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerendi ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</hi> The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. in <hi>Pſal. 47.</hi> Ambr. <hi>in</hi> Eph. <hi>2.20.</hi> Aug. <hi>in</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. c. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> and the Orthodox Modern, generally conſent.</p>
               <p>The Doctrinal concluſion, which theſe words of the Charter afford us, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the materials of particular viſible Churches, is, that,</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Concluſion.</hi> It is the will and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of Chriſt, that all and only ſuch grown perſons be admitted Members of particular Churches, who make ſuch a publick profeſſion of their Faith, as the Church may, in charitable diſcretion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, hath bleſſedneſs annexed to it, and is ſuch as fleſh and blood hath not revealed to a man, but our Heavenly Father.] 1. That Chriſt here meant a particular viſible Church, and not only the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, we have partly evinced alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and ſhall more fully hereafter. 2. That perſons meant by Chriſt here, are <hi>adulti,</hi> grown perſons, appeareth by his queſtions to the Apoſtles, <hi>Whom do men ſay?</hi> and, <hi>whom do ye ſay, that I am?</hi> and, by <hi>Peter's</hi> anſwer. As for Infants, they are indeed Members of the Church, and, as ſuch, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized; yet it is ſo, only as they are inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their Parents, by vertue of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41503:12"/> wherein they are wrapped with their Parents, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. 3. That ſuch <hi>adulti,</hi> or grown perſons, muſt make a publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith before the Lord and his people.] So Chriſt required <hi>Peter</hi> to do here, and, when he had ſo done, ſaid Chriſt, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Rock I will build my Church, viz.</hi> in after times. For no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Chriſtian Church was actually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, at this time, nor till after the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion of Chriſt, in <hi>Act.</hi> 1. <hi>q. d.</hi> Then take this courſe, and ever after, all the World over, if you will have a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church to be acknowledged by me to be my building. 4. That their Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Faith muſt be ſo made, as that the Church may, in charitable diſcretion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it to have bleſſedneſs annexed, &amp;c. For ſeeing it pleaſeth Chriſt to uſe Men as his Inſtruments in building his Church, <hi>Zach.</hi> 6.15. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12. He is content that they improve the judgement which they have. Chriſts judgement concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Peter</hi> was infallible; for <hi>he knew what was in man,</hi> John 2.25. But the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Members of the Church are but men, who <hi>judge by the outward appearance,</hi> 1 Sam. 16.7. Therefore their judgment is fallible, and hath been deceived; as we
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41503:13"/> ſee in the judgement of the Apoſtles and the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> concerning <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira;</hi> and in that of <hi>Philip,</hi> and the Church in <hi>Samaria</hi> concerning <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> &amp;c. Their duty is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed as far as men may, by Rule, with due moderation and gentleneſs, to try them, who offer themſelves to fellowſhip, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be Believers, or not; refuſing known Hypocrites; though when they have done all they can, cloſe Hypocrites will creep in. 5. That all they who hold forth ſuch a profeſſion of Faith, as the Church may, in charitable diſcretion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be true, are to be receiv'd.] Though ſome of them have been formerly ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, yet now holding forth repentance, they are to be received, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. and though ſome are at preſent, <hi>weak in Faith,</hi> yet, if we may conceive that the Lord hath received them, the Church muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.1, 3. For Chriſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d this confeſſion of <hi>Peter,</hi> though he was at preſent but weak in Faith, as the following Story in this Chapter, <hi>v.</hi> 22, 23. clearly ſheweth. 6. That none but ſuch be admitted into Church-fellowſhip. For this Chapter limits the Church, to accept only ſuch. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Rock will I build my Church. i. e.</hi> Chriſt believed on, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41503:13"/> publickly confeſſed. A meer verbal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion is not that Rock. For the Devils made ſuch a confeſſion of Chriſt, yet were not built on him, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.34. But this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of <hi>Peter</hi> was ſuch as held forth his Faith in him; as appears by Chriſt's three-fold Elogy, or praiſe of it. 1. From its effect. <hi>Bleſſed art thou,</hi> &amp;c, as, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.3. 2. From the procreant cauſe of it: <hi>Not fleſh and blood, but my Father hath revealed it,</hi> as <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25, 26. 3. From the title <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>Peter,</hi> before promiſed, <hi>John</hi> 1.42. and now confirmed to him, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying <hi>a Stone;</hi> whereby Chriſt, not only acknowledgeth his faith, and that he was thereby a living Stone, and fit to have a principal place in this Spiritual Building, (in which ſenſe, <hi>Peter</hi> applyeth a like title to other Believers, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4, 5. who yet were inferiour in degree to himſelf) but alſo giveth him this Prerogative and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that he ſhould be the firſt Planter of the Chriſtian Church, both amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> Act. 2. and the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> Act. 15.7.</p>
               <p>The Concluſion may be confirmed by two Arguments in the Text.</p>
               <p n="1">1. From the name whereby he calleth this holy Society, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) a <hi>Church; i. e. a company called out.</hi> Whence? ſee <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.19. To what?
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41503:14"/> See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. How? Not only by <hi>active vocation,</hi> by mans miniſtry, exhorting them to repent and believe: So ſundry are called, who are not, in the leaſt, wrought upon to anſwer that call, but put it off (as they who were invited to the great Supper, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.18.) with excuſe. Such are called, but no Church. Therefore more is required to qualifie for memberſhip of a viſible Church, <hi>viz. paſſive vocation,</hi> whereby they are wrought upon to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer Gods call, by ſubmiſſion thereunto, at leaſt, in outward profeſſion, though ſome do it but <hi>feinedly, Pſ.</hi> 18.44. Saints, by internal and inviſible calling, are ſuch, as anſwer Gods call inwardly and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually. Saints, by external and viſible cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, are ſubdued to yeeld obedience to the Word in viſible profeſſion. Thus, all that were called into the Vineyard, had ſo much efficacy of the Spirit in them, that they all came into the Vineyard, and laboured in it, though not with like ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity. <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. According to this clauſe of <hi>the Chapter,</hi> the Churches planted by the Apoſtles, were conſtituted, for the materials of them; elſe the Apoſtles could not have given both the<note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.2.</note> members and<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.1 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.27 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2 &amp; 6.16. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15</note> Churches ſuch high titles, as they did. Nor did they by theſe titles deſcribe the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41503:14"/> inviſible Church only, but viſible Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. For to ſuch, <hi>Paul</hi> wrote his Epiſtles: and the like expreſſions are applyed, in other texts, manifeſtly to viſible Churches. Nor do theſe titles deſcribe particular Churches only according to the better ſort of members, but ſuch they did, in the judgement of chriſtian charity, conceive all their members to be, as <hi>Paul</hi> told the Philippians, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.6, 7. which he could not have ſaid if he had not known the care of the Church, in admitting per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons into memberſhip with them, to be according to the concluſion noted by us.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> From Chriſt's appropriating ſuch a particular Church to himſelf, owning it for his <hi>[my Church] q. d.</hi> I own any Church thus built by my ſelf to be my Church; according to that in <hi>Act.</hi> 2.47. <hi>The Lord added to the Church daily ſuch as ſhould be ſaved. The Lord added them.</hi> How? Not only by giving them ſaving faith, and ſo adding them to the inviſible Church, but alſo by his inclining their hearts to offer themſelves unto the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the viſible Church, and to profeſs their faith before them: and by bowing the hearts of the Apoſtles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Brethren to receive them into viſible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41503:15"/> of viſible Ordinances; as appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>v.</hi> 41, 42. Thus he added them, <hi>daily to the Church;</hi> which cleares it to be an act of the Lords ordinary diſpenſation, and therefore preſidential to the Churches in their ordinary practice. They, who were thus added, are ſaid to be ſuch <hi>as ſhould be ſaved.</hi> That is; they were ſuch, either in the judgment of the Lord, which is infallible; or in the judgment of the Church, which is fallible. The Church looked at them, according to their fruits, <hi>viz.</hi> their profeſſion of faith, and their Chriſtian converſation, obſerving ſo much in both, that they ſaw reaſon, in charity guided by rule, to conceive them to be in a ſtate of Salvation. Such were the three thouſand ſpoken of in <hi>v.</hi> 41. as appeared by their affectionate and ſubmiſſive inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Apoſtles, whom <hi>they mocked</hi> before, what they ſhould <hi>do to be ſaved,</hi> being <hi>pricked in their hearts. v.</hi> 37. and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, by <hi>their gladly receiving the Word;</hi> both of promiſe, for themſelves and their Children, with faith; and of precept, to <hi>repent</hi> and <hi>be baptized,</hi> and to <hi>ſave themſelves from that froward generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> with obedience. True it is, that they could not in one day make ſo large ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts of Gods work upon them, as are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41503:15"/> commonly held forth in our Churches: nor do we effect too large narrations, but wiſh ſuch paſſages, as are ſuperfluous, left out: And at that time, leſs was needful to be expreſſed, than neceſſity calls for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, ordinarily. For the Apoſtles had a more quick Spiritual diſcerning, than ordinary Officers and Churches have. And concerning the three thouſand, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. the manner of their offering them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Church-fellowſhip, viſibly at ſuch a time, when ſuch viſible confeſſion of Chriſt was with manifeſt hazzard to their lives, gave good ground to the Apoſtles and the Brethren, of conceiving charitably, that they were all of them in a ſtate of Salvation, and ſuch as the Lord himſelf added to the Church. In theſe places and times, where Church-fellowſhip is an honour, and drawes after it ſundry out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and worldly advantages, it will be neceſſary, that the Church be ſatisfied, as by ſufficient teſtimony concerning their good converſation, ſo by their holding forth their confeſſion of faith, both <hi>quae creditur,</hi> and <hi>quâ creditur,</hi> of the Doctrine of Faith, and of the Gift of Faith, how it was wrought, and how it works in them. As Mr. <hi>Rogers,</hi> in his Treatiſe of Faith, ſaith it may be known of men by thoſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41503:16"/> tryals. And this care ſuits the nature of Church-power, which is delegate and ſtewardly. For, as the faithfulneſs of a Steward bindeth him to receive none in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Lords family, but according to his Lords mind and appointment; ſo the faithfulneſs of the Church unto Chriſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeth them to receive ſuch into this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fellowſhip, as they may, in charitable diſcretion, conceive, the Lord receiveth and addeth thereunto.</p>
               <p>Againſt what hath been ſaid, two ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections are made,</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> Obj. <hi>Chriſt received</hi> Judas, <hi>whom he knew to be a hypocrite, into fellowſhip of the twelve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Not into a particular viſible Church; for no ſuch was then gathered. 2. Chriſt had a peculiar reaſon for it, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> doth not concern Churches, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.18.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> Obj. 2. <hi>Chriſt himſelf compareth viſible Churches, to a Field, wherein are Tares; to a Draw-N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, which gathers good and bad Fiſhes; to ten Virgins, of which five were fooliſh; and the Churches planted by the Apoſtles had in them ſundry Hypocrites, and ſcandalous perſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Such places ſhew, 1. That in viſible Churches ſometimes Hypocrites are mixed, either by the ſleepineſs, and fault of thoſe that ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>vent it:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41503:16"/> Thence the Tares: or by the wylineſs of Hypocrites, who creep in unawares, <hi>Jude</hi> 4. as the bad Fiſh came into the net under water: or they pretend ſaving gifts, as the five fooliſh Virgins; ſo, falſe Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.4. 2. The pureſt Churches may be blemiſhed with ſcandals, till they can orderly proceed againſt them; but then they muſt be caſt out. Therfore they knew not that they were ſuch before.</p>
               <p>From this 2d concluſion, thus explained and confirmed, we may infer as followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſect. </seg>1</label> If this be ſo; then more is required, as the eſſential property of Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, as viſible, than that they profeſs before men the Faith, crave fellowſhip with the viſible Church, and deſire the viſible ſeals of the Covenant. For men may have all theſe three properties, who are notoriouſly ſcandalous in their lives, Drunkards, Adulterers, prophane Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Curſers; in a word, ſuch as are deſcribed, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2, 3, 4. <hi>Who have a form of Godlineſs, denying the power of it,</hi> concerning whom the Apoſtle's charge is, <hi>from ſuch turn away, v.</hi> 5. If in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary converſe, the People of God muſt not exerciſe needleſs familiarity with ſuch: much leſs may they receive them into ſpiritual fellowſhip and fraternity.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41503:17"/> If ſuch, being Members, muſt be caſt out, certainly, being out of Church-fellowſhip, they may not be received in, whileſt they continue ſuch.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſect. </seg>2</label> If Chriſt will build his Church upon this Rock; then it is the bounden duty of Churches to ſee, ſo far as they can ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to rule, that all whom they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive into Church-fellowſhip, be viſible Believers, ſuch as have been deſcribed in the Concluſion above propounded, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, and proved; leſt otherwiſe they build without a foundation. Particularly; 1. They are to ſee, ſo far as in charity they may diſcern, that they are Beleivers in Chriſt; Elſe, they cannot anſwer the titles given them in Scripture, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4, 5. nor the praiſes given unto <hi>Peter</hi> ſo confeſſing Chriſt, that Chriſt ſaid, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Rock I will build my Church.</hi> 2. They are to ſee, that they profeſs their Faith and Holineſs in a good converſation, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.27. <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.12, 13. For they that <hi>profeſs they know God, but in their works deny him, are abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, Tit.</hi> 1.16. 3. And in a publick confeſſion of their faith before the Church, as <hi>Peter</hi> did here before Chriſt and the Apoſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Only, becauſe the Church cannot ſee the heart immediately, as Chriſt did <hi>Peter's,</hi> the confeſſion of faith made
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41503:17"/> to men muſt hold forth the gift of faith, as well as the doctrine of faith. So <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> underſtood thoſe words, <hi>Sanctifie the Lord God in your hearts, and be ready al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to give an anſwer to every man that asketh you a reaſon of the hope that is in you.</hi> 1 Pet. 3.15. Calvin's note upon it, is this;<note n="‖" place="margin">Ejus, quae in vobis eſt, ſpei.] Spes hîc, per <hi>ſynech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dochen,</hi> pro fide capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di debet ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duló quod dicit. Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificat n. eam dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>confeſſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> probari Deo, quae ex corde emanat; quia, niſi intus reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deat fides, fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>à gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gua. Ergo radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis agat, ut deinde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferat Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſionis fructum. <hi>Calv.</hi> in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Hope, here, is, by a Synechdoche, put for faith. What he ſaith, ought to be diligently weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For it ſignifieth, that God approveth only that confeſſion, which proceeds out of the heart: becauſe unleſs faith reſide within, the tongue will babble in vain. Therefore faith muſt be rooted in us, that afterward it may bring forth the fruit of confeſſion.</hi> And, when all this is done, the Brethren are to conſent in receiving them, and herein to ſhew forth the gentleneſs of Chriſt (who <hi>will not break a bruiſed reed, nor quench ſmoking flax</hi>) in giving due encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the weak in faith, if they ſee cauſe to conceive, by rightly ordered charity, that the root of the matter is in them. But, if they ſee juſt cauſe to doubt of that, they have warrant to ſuſpend their accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, till better ſatisfaction be given, from the primitive pattern, in <hi>Act.</hi> 9.26. However, the Officers muſt propound it to the Brethren, to declare, whether they are ſo far ſatisfied with what they have
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41503:18"/> heard, that they do conſent that ſuch ſhall be received into their fellowſhip; as <hi>Peter</hi> put a like queſtion to the Brethren that went with him from <hi>Joppa,</hi> concerning the Baptizing of <hi>Cornelius</hi> and thoſe with him, upon whom the Holy Ghoſt fell viſibly, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.44, 45, 46. &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſect. </seg>3</label> 3. <hi>Conſ.</hi> If upon this Rock [Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved on, and publickly confeſſed, by grown perſons] the Church of Chriſt is to be built; then the Children of the Church, who were Baptized in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, when they come to be of ripe age, muſt hold forth publickly their perſonal confeſſion of Faith, that they may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Lords Table, and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in Voting and in Elections and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, in their own perſonal right. But, if they be found groſly ignorant, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, or profeſſing a falſe faith, or deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the true Faith, or contemners of Church-fellowſhip, and the Ordinances of Chriſt, or do not, according to this clauſe of the Charter, publickly profeſs their faith, and crave Church-fellowſhip, they may not be owned for Members, by their admiſſion unto the Lord's Table, and unto other priviledges of Church-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, in their own right, but are to be declared non-members. In <hi>Jacobs</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41503:18"/> when the Lord brought them to <hi>Canaan,</hi> that ſtanding Ordinance of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting unto the Lord, before the Prieſt, their firſt fruits, every year, with ſuch a ſolemn confeſſion made by all grown Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, as is appointed in <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.2 to 16. was a viſible profeſſion of their Faith and Obedience, ſuited to the condition of that Church and time, in performance whereof, they <hi>avouched the Lord to be their God, and to walk in his wayes, and keep his Statutes, and his Commandments, and his Judgments, and to hearken unto his Voice: and the Lord avouched them to be his peculiar People,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>v.</hi> 16, 17, 18. And the like, if not greater, care was had of the profeſſion and converſation of the Sons of ſtrangers, the Children of ſuch Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes, as were admitted into the Church of Iſrael, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.6, 7. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> alſo requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all, whom he admitted unto his Baptiſme, a repenting-confeſſion of their ſins, and that they ſhould believe on him which ſhould come after him, that is, on Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.4. warning them, not to reſt in this, that <hi>Abraham</hi> was their Father, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.9. Anſwerably, the Primitive Churches required of all grown perſons, 1. Viſible Repentance, in caſe of open ſcandals, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.18. 2. to joyn there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41503:19"/> a publick profeſſion of their Faith in Chriſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.39. 3. A profeſſion of their ſubjection to the Goſpel of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13. And after the Apoſtles dayes, the ancient Churches, they had their <hi>Poeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> ſuch as held forth their Repentance publickly; and their <hi>Catechumeni,</hi> who were of two ſorts, 1. Such as had been Pagans, and were inſtructed by being catechized in the Chriſtian Faith, that they might crave Baptiſme when they ſhould be found fit, and then were called <hi>Competentes:</hi> In the interim, they were called <hi>Audientes,</hi> or, <hi>Auditores.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tertull.</hi> l. de poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. c. 6. &amp; praeſcr. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. c. 4. <hi>Cypr.</hi> l. 3. ep. 17.</note> 2. Such as having been Baptized in their Infancy, when they did <hi>nonnihil adoleſcere,</hi> were Catechized, and being found to be Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, were confirmed by impoſition of Hands, and admitted unto the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and unto the full fruition of all Church-priviledges. Theſe, <hi>Clemens</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>Incipientes</hi> &amp; <hi>Novitios,</hi> and ſo do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, from 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. As the Myſtery of Iniquity wrought higher and more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually to adva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce Papal uſurpation, by the ſpoils of Churches, this cuſtom, in the right uſe of it, ceaſed; and Popery retained only the name of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> but cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the thing, and turned it into a Sacrament, limiting the Adminiſtration
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41503:19"/> of it to Dioceſan Praelats. This corrupt cuſtom was continued in <hi>England,</hi> after they renounced the Pope. But, as <hi>Luther</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> ſought to introduce the right uſe of it into the Churches there; So did <hi>Cranmer,</hi> under that Godly King <hi>Edward the</hi> 6th, endeavour in <hi>England,</hi> and committed the peruſal and cenſure of the Common-Prayer-Book, to that godly, learned and moderate Theologue, <hi>Bucer;</hi> who examining the Book, found, among ſundry other things, <q>That thoſe which were to be confirmed,<note place="margin">Cenſura M. <hi>Buceri</hi> ſuper lib. Ordinat. Eccleſ. cap. 17.</note> muſt ſay the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed, the Lord's Prayer, and the ten Commandments, and anſwer the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſhort Catechiſm. <hi>Bucer</hi>'s cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure upon it is thus: This requires di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent ponderation. If they think it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, that the words of this Confeſſion be recited, God abhorreth ſuch as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs him in words, and their heart is far from him. Nor is Catechizing inſtituted to this end, that they ſhould anſwer in words only, That they believe in God, and will keep his Commandments. The Lord ſaith, Teach them to obſerve and do, and not only to ſpeak; and he requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſuch Worſhippers, as worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth. But, if a true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith, and profeſſion of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41503:20"/> ſuch as ſhould be required of <hi>adulti,</hi> grown perſons, unto Baptiſm, be meant; ſuch a Confeſſion of Faith muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, as may be judged, not to be born in the mouth, or gotten only by humane teaching, but alſo it muſt have thoſe ſignes in the life and manners, that it ought to be received of the Churches, <hi>as coming from an heart truly believing the Goſpel, and the Doctrine of the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi>
                  </q> For though the Church cannot look into the hearts of men, yet they ought to judge of trees by their fruits: which fruits, afterwards, he declares at large. But I haſten to the next point, having been the larger in this, becauſe it is a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of no leſs importance than diſpute, in reference to the queſtion under ſo much agitation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Concerning the formal Cauſe.</head>
               <p>THe formall cauſe, or that which gives eſſential being to this Church, is here held forth in a Metaphor, taken from houſes. For, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, properly ſignifies, to build an houſe of materials,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41503:20"/> fitly joyned and compacted together: but Chriſt doth not here ſpeak of the ſtructure of a material houſe, but of the conſtitut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that holy Society, which he calleth <hi>his Church,</hi> under the metaphor of build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an houſe, which every way ſuits the matter he ſpeaks of. For, as a material houſe (ſuppoſe, of ſtones) is built by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly placing and ſtrongly cementing them together, which before were either ſcattered ſtones, or a confuſed and looſe heape, but not an houſe, till they were thus framed and compacted together: ſo this holy Society, the Church of Chriſt, ariſeth from the coadunition, or knitting together of many Saints into one, by an holy Covenant, whereby they, <hi>as lively Stones, are built up a ſpiritual Houſe,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4, 5. And as the natural body of a man is built, by an orderly joyning and firmly knitting the parts together: So is the Church of Chriſt built by the mutual Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting of the Saints, the Members of the Church, which is called the Body of Chriſt, where the Members of it are thus orderly and firmly knit to the Head, and one to another. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.15, 16. The ſame holds in Cities and Families, which are thus built alſo; and therefore the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of this matter, under the ſame
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41503:21"/> matephor, in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.19, 20, 21. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion from hence is, that</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>3</label> It is the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt, our Lord, that his Churches, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the New Teſtament, be conſtituted, in reſpect of their eſſential form, by the publick mutual covenanting of the Saints, with the Lord, and one with another.</p>
               <p>Though all men ſeem to grant, that every Church of Chriſt hath its being from a Covenant (for which cauſe, they that want an explicite Covenant, do yet plead their implicite Covenant to maintain the truth of their Church-ſtate) yet ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes are raiſed againſt the Church Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, that I am compelled to handle this point alſo the more largely, that the truth concerning it, may be the better cleared and ſetled. I ſhall therefore, with the help of Chriſt, ſhew, 1. To what end it ſerveth; 2. what it imports; 3. prove it to be the Ordinance of Chriſt; 4. draw ſome conſectaries from the Concluſion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The next end of their confederating is, to engage themſelves to ſubmit one to another in the Lord, &amp; to cleave to <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Rules, and to one another in him, mutually, and to walk together, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, in the uſe of all means ſanctified and appointed by him for attaining the ends of Church-communion.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:41503:21"/>2. The Covenant it ſelf imports two things, 1. On the Lords part, it implyeth, (1.) the Lords giving them his Covenant for themſelves and their ſeed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. (2.) His giving them hearts to take hold of his Covenant, accordingly, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.4, 5, 6, 7. where you ſee, the Eunuch's and the ſon of the ſtranger's taking hold of the Covenant, is fore-told, as that which ſhould be previous to the Lord's <hi>giving them a place in his houſe, and bringing them into his holy Mountain</hi> (that is, joyning them to his viſible Churches under the New Teſtament) when the Church <hi>ſhall be called, an houſe of prayer to all Nations, v.</hi> 7. 2. On the Saints part; their cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting for themſelves, and for their ſeed, to be the Lord's People, and to walk in his waies, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.10, 11, 12. and to cleave firmly one to another, <hi>viz.</hi> to their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Brethren, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.19. <hi>Neh.</hi> 10.29. with mutual watchfulneſs one over another, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.17. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.18. with <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.15, 16. and with mutual ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Chriſt, and to one another, in him. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Such Covenanting is Chriſt's Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance unto the Churches under the New Teſtament; this is proved,</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> From the parity of reaſon between the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41503:22"/> Churches before the coming of Chriſt and ſince, in all eſſentials of a Church. For in the eſſential ſtate and form of a Church, there is <hi>par ratio omnium Eccleſiarum.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the coming of Chriſt, the People of God were joined together into Church-fellowſhip by confederation; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.5. <hi>Gather my Saints together unto me; thoſe that have made a Covenant with me by ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice.</hi> So did <hi>Adam,</hi> and all the holy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs, unto <hi>Abraham:</hi> and ſo did the poſterity of <hi>Jacob,</hi> at Mount <hi>Sinai, Exod.</hi> 19.5, 6. and 24.8. and from thence were called, <hi>the Church in the Wilderneſs,</hi> with which <hi>Moſes</hi> was joyned. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.38. And ſo, the Lord there tells them, it ſhould be in point of the Covenant, though not of Sacrifices, with the Church under the New Teſtament, <hi>v.</hi> 14, 15, 16. In <hi>Abrahams</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, God built his Church by a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, without ſacrifice; but firſt, the Lord changed his name, and called him <hi>Abraham,</hi> to ſhew, that he now treated with him, not as a ſingle perſon, but as a Father of many nations, and as a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude vertually, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.5. Then he gave him his Covenant, to be a God to him, and his ſeed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. and, to ſhew that it was a Church-Covenant, he gave him Circumciſion for the viſible ſigne and ſeal
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41503:22"/> of it. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10-15. Thus far went the Covenant on God's part. 2. On <hi>Abraham's</hi> part; he firſt accepted both the Covenant and the confirmation of it, with Faith and holy reverence, declared by his rejoycing, <hi>John.</hi> 8.56. and humble proſtration of himſelf before the Lord, <hi>v.</hi> 17. and by real performance of it, after, both in his own perſon, being circumciſed when he was ninty nine years old, <hi>v.</hi> 24. and, as a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet and Ruler, inſtructing his family, concerning the Covenant and Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and their duty to accept the one, and ſubmit to the other, which they did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, <hi>v.</hi> 23, 27. and thereby profeſſed their ſubjection to the Lord and to his Ordinances. Hence the poſterity of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> by <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> became the Lord's People, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.7. yea his <hi>firſt born, Exod.</hi> 4.22, 23. and had Circumciſion as a ſeal of this Covenant, whereby they were diſtinguiſhed from all other People, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.6, 7, 8. But they, like men, tranſgreſſed and broke the Covenant, both in <hi>Egpyt,</hi> and in the Wilderneſs: yet the Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faithful in his Covenant unto their forefathers, did not caſt them off, but cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them to repentance, and renewed his Covenant, in a more Evangelical man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, in the plains of <hi>Moab,</hi> that he might
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41503:23"/> eſtabliſh them to be his People, and their little ones, and the ſtrangers, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.10-14. which Covenant they took hold of, for themſelves and their ſeed, and for them that were not there with them, that day, <hi>v.</hi> 15. that they would admit none unto Church-fellowſhip with them, but ſuch as ſhould ſeparate themſelves from the polutions of the Heathen, and enter into the common engagement with them, to cleave to the Lord, and to one another, with member-like love, watchfulneſs and ſubmiſſion mutually. Hence it was, that the ſin of one <hi>Achan</hi> became the ſin and puniſhment of all Iſrael, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7.11, 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> From the Apoſtles manner of planting Chriſtian Churches, after the Death, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and Aſcenſion of Chriſt. Their cuſtom it was, when they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted many to Chriſt, to joyn them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether into one Congregation, by cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting with the Lord and his People, for themſelves and their Children.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Againſt this aſſertion, ſome object, that in the planting of the Church at</hi> Samaria, <hi>in</hi> Cornelius <hi>his houſe, at</hi> Phillippi, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth, Epheſus, Theſſalonica, &amp;c. <hi>they find no mention of ſuch a Covenant as the Doctrine intendeth, only that they believed, profeſſed, and were Baptiſed, but no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41503:23"/> of an expreſs vocal Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> 1. Though it be not mentioned in thoſe Texts, yet it may be in others. 2. We need not be ſolicitous about the words, if the thing be found there. 3. And that the thing is to be found there, it may be evinced three wayes: 1. From their being bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. 2. From the phraſes. 3. From the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes, which import their covenanting together. 1. From their being baptized, which preſuppoſeth, that they were firſt made Diſciples, becauſe their Commiſſion required that, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. where, <hi>to make Diſciples,</hi> is as much as to gather and plant Churches, by viſible bringing men into Chriſts ſchool, with engagement, by thoſe of years, for themſelves and their ſeed, to ſubmit unto Chriſts teaching and government therein. This ſchool of Chriſt is the Church of God, whence the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſtian Churches are called, <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi> in <hi>Act.</hi> 15.10. So then, they were in Church-fellowſhip, before they were baptiſed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From the Phraſes, which imply covenanting to be that, whereby they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came viſible members of the Church. I ſhall inſtance in two. The firſt is uſed in <hi>Act.</hi> 2.41. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>were added;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 47. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the Lord added:</hi> and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41503:24"/> 
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 5.14. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>were the more added.</hi> The word imports ſuch an adding as did viſibly and firmly knit them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Calvin</hi> in <hi>Act 2.41.</hi> adjuncti Chriſti di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipulis, vel in i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem corpus inſiti.</note> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith, <hi>they were joyned to Chriſts Diſciples, or ingrafted into the ſame body.</hi> That which thus viſibly ingrafted them, was not Gods working Faith in their hearts, or their viſible profeſſion of it: for it is ſaid, <hi>Believers, were added. v.</hi> 14. which is of the ſame import with, <hi>thoſe that gladly received the Word,</hi> in <hi>Act.</hi> 2.41. Therefore this adding was by ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe; and what could that be, but their viſible taking hold of the Covenant with that particular Chriſtian Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereunto they now joyned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves notwithſtanding their former ſtate in the National Church of the Jewes? And that they were thus added to the Church, <hi>Luke</hi> confirmeth two wayes. 1. by the effect of this ingagement, in <hi>Act.</hi> 2.42. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>they were ſtrongly and conſtantly knit together</hi> (viz. by vertue of their former mutual ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) <hi>in the Apoſtles Doctrine,</hi> Hearing, Believing, Profeſſing, Obeying it conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; <hi>and in fellowſhip, i. e.</hi> in Church Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, into which they were combined and compacted before, having ſolemnly <hi>given up themſelves, firſt to the Lord, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41503:24"/> then to the Apoſtles and Church, by the will of God,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> expoundeth it, in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. 2. <hi>Luke</hi> confirmeth the ſame ſenſe of their being <hi>added to the Church,</hi> by expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the manner of it to be ſo, as <hi>of the reſt durſt no man joyn himſelf to them,</hi> in <hi>Act.</hi> 5.13. <hi>yet they did magnifie them, i. e.</hi> they approved their doctrine and way, and confeſſed the truth and goodneſs of it. All which was not ſufficient to add them ſo to the Church, as believers were added, <hi>viz.</hi> by publick voluntary engagement with the Church, mutually. And this to be the meaning, <hi>Luke</hi> confirmeth, by uſing another word, ſynonomous with this, which more plainly expreſſeth the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their being added to the Church, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to be glewed:</hi> which word, though it ſometimes ſignifieth joyning, in a more common and lax ſenſe, yet not in matters of this nature. Therefore, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Tertullian's</hi> rule, <hi>Deligendus eſt ſenſus è materiâ dicti:</hi> and then we know, that all joyning unto a Corporation, muſt be done by Covenant, as it is in Marriage, and voluntary ſervices, to both which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations the ſame Verb is applied; to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.5. to voluntary ſervice, in <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.15. both which are by voluntary covenant. This is the ſtrong knitting glew
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41503:25"/> whereby perſons are joyned together in all ſuch voluntary relations. So much may ſerve for explication of the phraſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third proof is from the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes uſed in the New Teſtament, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs their covenanting together. The Church is compar'd to a Houſe, to the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy-natural, to a Body-corporate, to a Wife.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To an <hi>Houſe,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. the whole ſociety is called, <hi>the houſhold of Faith, Gal.</hi> 6.10. every member of it is ſaid to be, <hi>of the Houſhold of God, Eph.</hi> 2.19. Whether you ſpeak of an Houſe, in an Architecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical ſenſe, the materials muſt be cemented together; now, in the Church, that ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the Covenant; or, in an oeconomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſenſe, the Members that are voluntarily added, as voluntary Servants to the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, are joyned with the reſt by Covenant; ſo it muſt be in the Church, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.21.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To the Natural-body, in man; the Head of it is Jeſus Chriſt, the Members are Beleivers, the whole is made up eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially, when they are harmonically joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſtrongly compacted together by mutual engagement to ſubmit one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in the Lord, whereby they fall, as it were into joynts; as the Thigh falleth into the Knee, and the Shoulder into the Shoulder-blade, by ſhooting it ſelf into the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41503:25"/> hollow of it, and is firmly knit to it, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.15, 16.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To a Body-Corporate. Hence the Church is called <hi>the holy City, Rev.</hi> 11.2. and Church-members, <hi>Citizens with the Saints, Epheſ.</hi> 2.19. That whereby the Church is as <hi>a City compacted</hi> together, is the Covenant. For as all Citizens are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into <hi>jus Civitatis,</hi> and become free Denizens, by voluntary entering into the common engagement and covenant, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they become a Political-body; ſo it is in the Church.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To a Wife, whether eſpouſed or married. All eſpouſals and marriages, are by a voluntary mutual Covenant, <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.14. So it is in the Church of God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.5. Hence <hi>Paul</hi> ſtileth the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church at <hi>Corinth, a Virgin eſpouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. To ſhew that all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers were joyned, as one Virgin, into one body, and that Virgin-Church, into a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of eſpouſals with Jeſus Chriſt, as their Head and Husband, in all his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and one with another, in him, mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally. Thus, we ſee, the phraſes and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes, in the New Teſtament, do ſtrongly confirm this truth, That the firſt Chriſtian Churches planted by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, were conſtituted, in reſpect of their
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41503:26"/> eſſential form, in one body among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſeverally and reſpectively, by an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Covenant. If any demand, why the Apoſtles did not expreſly mention the word, <hi>Covenant.</hi> Two reaſons are given for that; 1. That it was not neceſſary; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it had been ſo clearly and fully expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the old Teſtament, as that which gives eſſential being to the Church. And it is uſual in Scripture, that duties, which are grounded upon a natural, or moral, and common reaſon and equity, and have been largely expreſſed in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are but briefly and implicitely point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at in the New: as the Baptizing of Infants, the Chriſtian Sabbath, and the manner of ſanctifying it; ſo this of the Church-Covenant. Yet concerning all theſe, ſufficient light is held forth in the New Teſtament, for manifeſting the mind of God unto his People.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That it was not ſeaſonable and ſafe for the Churches, then living under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Princes and Rulers, enemies to Chriſt, unto whoſe jealouſies the name of <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> and <hi>Covenanters</hi> might render them obnoxious, and might ſeem dangerous to the civil peace. Therefore Chriſt and his Apoſtles choſe rather to forbear mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the name, yet eſtabliſhed the thing
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41503:26"/> under ſuch ſimilitudes and parables, as might hide it from others, and yet reveal it to the Saints.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> From the voluntary relation, which is between the Members of the Church, together with their mutual intereſt one in another, and their mutual power one over another; all which do neceſſarily imply their mutual covenanting one with another. 1. Their relation is voluntary: and all voluntary relations are by cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; as, between a Society or Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Members of it; between Husbands and Wives; between Maſters and voluntary Servants: So, between a Church and the Members of it; both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, before, were free, the one, to offer himſelf into fellowſhip, or not; the other, to admit him, or not. If ſuch joyn toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is by their free conſent, and muſt be by mutual engagement. Hence ariſeth their ſpecial and particular relation to this Church, and among themſelves mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, as a body diſtinct from other Churches. 2. Their intereſt one in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and power one over another mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, ariſeth from their mutual engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by covenant. No Church can judge any inhabitant among them, unleſs he firſt give up himſelf to the Lord and them, in a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41503:27"/> profeſſed ſubjectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the Goſpel of Chriſt. Nor can any inhabitant expect member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like watchfulneſs and helpfulneſs from the Church, unleſs, upon his offering himſelf to enter into the common ingagement, they receive him, and take upon them that care over him. 3. Their conſtant fellowſhip in Church-priviledges, ariſeth from this mutual ingagement by Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. For none can be admitted unto them, without conſent of the body: nor can the body admit them thereunto, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their taking hold of the Covenant: for, till then, they are not under the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the whole; as it hath been prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>There ſeems to be no need of Church-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, ſeeing the Covenant of Grace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigheth to Beleivers all Spiritual bleſſings, and bindeth them to all Chriſtian duties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> The Spiritual bleſſings communicated by Chriſt unto Believers, through the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, are of two ſorts. 1. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, <hi>viz.</hi> Adoption, Juſtification, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, &amp;c. together with the bleſſed right unto all the outward good things of this life, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. and a remote or medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate right unto Church-priviledges. Theſe, all Believers have from Chriſt by the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, as they are Believers in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41503:27"/> ſincerity and truth, in the ſight of God. 2. External, <hi>viz.</hi> Church-fellowſhip, and power of the Keys, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe, viſible Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers have from Chriſt, through the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, as they are confederates, and joyned with the Church by taking hold of the Covenant. This difference is between them; The former are limited to the perſons of true Believers in the ſight of God, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.4. The latter are given to a ſociety of true Believers, in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Church, and are extended to their ſeed alſo, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.6.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though the Covenant of Grace re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by us, binds us to all Chriſtian du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties required in the Goſpel, yet it bindes us alſo to do them in the due order: for God is the God of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rder, and not of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. Therefore ſuch duties as iſſue from voluntary relations, muſt be done only by thoſe who ſtand in ſuch relations. Will any Man or Woman infer from his or her being in the Covenant of Grace, that therefore there is no need or uſe of a conjugal Covenant, but that he hath right to all Women, and ſhe to all Men, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form conjugal duties with them, where ever they come, though they are not joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to any of them by a conjugal Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant? The like reaſon is of all other du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41503:28"/> which are founded in other volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary relations; as between Maſters and Servants, Paſtor and People, Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and the Members of them, particular Churches and their Members. Therefore the Covenant of Grace binds all Believers to ſuch mutual covenanting together, as is neceſſary for the orderly diſcharge of the ſeveral duties that are to be performed by vertue of ſuch a ſtate and relation. Thus the concluſion is proved.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Coral∣lary. </seg>1</label> Hence it will follow, that it is not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to make one a viſible member of this or that Church, that he is joyned to it in hearty affection, or in neighbourhood of habitation, or in ordinary hearing the Word preached among them. For, 1. the members of ſeveral Churches may be ſo joyned; yea, 2. they that are members of no particular Church, may ſo joyn with Church aſſemblies. All theſe might be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed of thoſe who durſt not joyn as members, to the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem, Act.</hi> 5.13. And of that Heathen <hi>Corinthian,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.24, 25. 3. All theſe may be found in an excommunicate.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Coral∣lary. </seg>2</label> Then Baptiſm and profeſſion of the doctrine of Faith, with freedom from pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſcandal, do not formally conſtitute a Church, nor make one a viſible member of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41503:28"/> the Church. 1. Not Baptiſm; 1. becauſe the form muſt be before the <hi>formatum,</hi> not after it: but the Congregational-Church is before Baptiſm. For, 1. Baptiſm can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ordinarily be orderly adminiſtred, but by a Miniſter called unto Office by the Church. 2. Becauſe Baptiſm ſealeth the Covenant, and incorporation of a Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and his ſeed into the viſible Church. 1 Cor. 12, 13. Therefore Baptiſm is not before, but after the Church: Becauſe where the form is, there the <hi>formatum</hi> muſt be alſo. But viſible Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip may ceaſe by excommunication or deſertion, or by the diſſolution of a Church; yet Baptiſm remaineth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Not profeſſion of the Doctrine of Faith, though accompanied with free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from ſcandalous ſins. For general profeſſion cannot appropriate a man par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to any one Church, without particular ingagement to that particular body. 2. Nor doth it bring any one under the power of this or that Church, which it hath over its own Members, and other Churches have not. 3. If that were ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient; a man ſhould become a member of any particular Church whether it will or no.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Coral∣lary. </seg>3</label> Then a Member of one particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41503:29"/> is not, thereby, a Member of all viſible Congregations on earth. For, though a Church-covenant be common to all Churches, in its general nature; yet there is a ſpeciall combination, which gives a peculiar being to one Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal-Church and its members, diſtinct from all others. Elſe, how could one Church have that power over its own Members, which another hath not? And in all voluntary covenants, the only diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between them is, the peculiar intereſt which one hath in another, by a particular ingagement that paſſeth between party and party. Covenants of Corporations, of Marriages, of Service, and the like, are, in general, common to all that are in thoſe and the like relations; Yet, in particular appropriation, bind them only to this or that individual. No man can claim a memberlike right in all Corporations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is in covenant with one, upon this plea, that Corporation-covenants are common to all Societies: nor can an Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band plead, that he hath a conjugal right in all Wives, becauſe conjugal-covenant is common to all married perſons. The ſame holds in Churches, which are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed one from another by their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Covenants. Other abſurdities that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41503:29"/> proceed from this Tenet, I ſhall preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Coral∣lary. </seg>4</label> Then the Children of the Church, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their memberſhip, which they had, during their menority, by their Parents covenant; yet they muſt, when they are grown up, joyn themſelves to the Church by their voluntary taking hold of the Covenant publickly with the Church, in their own perſonal right, before they may be admitted to exerciſe all acts of Church-communion, and to partake of all Church-priviledges for themſelves, and before their Children may be Baptized. 1. I ſay, before they may be admitted to exerciſe all acts of Church-communion, and to partake of all Church-priviledges, for themſelves.] For, in their minority, they were Members in their Parents, and were Baptized, to ſeal the Covenant made with them in their Parents, or, with the Parents, for themſelves and their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. But when they come to years, they muſt take hold of the Covenant with the Church, for themſelves, becauſe now they are capable of Church-priviledges, in that way which they were not before. If any oppoſe againſt this, that Church-member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <hi>non recipit magis et minus;</hi> that argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth only, that one of the confederates is
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41503:30"/> no more engaged to the other, than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to him: But otherwiſe, in Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies, ſome are allowed greater liberties than others be, according to the diverſity of the ſubjects, and their capacities. So it is in Civil Societies and Corporations; the Child of the free-man of <hi>London,</hi> hath all the benefit of a free-mans Child, under age; he may trade for himſelf with and under his Father, in his Fathers right: But being of years, he may not ſet up ſhop, nor trade in his own right, till he firſt take up his freedom, and, by oath, voluntarily ſubmit himſelf to all the orders of that Society, and duty of a Citizen. Some think, that the Children of Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates are ſo compleat members, that they ſhould be excommunicated, in caſe of demerit. I cannot eaſily aſſent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: for that would imply, that they have an immediate right in all Church-priviledges, which I do not grant, nor believe; but that, as the Church looks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them <hi>tanquam in lumbis parentum;</hi> ſo alſo, if the grown Members of the Church obſerve vicious qualities and practiſes in them, they do not deal with them imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately in thoſe ſteps of proceeding, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. to bring matters to the Church, but they deal with their Parents
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41503:30"/> to diſcharge their duty, in educating their Children according to the rule, in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.4. To this ſenſe Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> applyeth that text, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14.<note place="margin">Ameſ. <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulla The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olog. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 32. <hi>art.</hi> 12, 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Infantes tamen non adeò perfecta ſunt membra Eccleſiae, ut poſſint actus Communionis exercere, aut ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitti ad omnia ejus privilegia participanda, niſi priùs incrementum fidei appareat: ab iis vero, quae pertinent ad initium fidei, et in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsum in Eccleſiam, non ſunt excludendi.</hi> 2. Nor may their Children be baptized, till themſelves have taken hold of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with the Church, in their own right. For, the Children of Church-members, when they come to age, for not taking hold of the Covenant with the Church, do become non-members, and are to be ſo looked at by the Church, if they deſert Church-fellowſhip (either departing from them in place, as <hi>Eſau</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mount <hi>Seir,</hi> or withdrawing from their communion;) or if the Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from them. In ſuch caſes, they are not ſo much as implicitely members. Therefore their Children may not be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized. For the right that Infants have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Baptiſm, is in their next and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Parents. 1. Becauſe the Apoſtle, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. doth ſo limit it. 2. Becauſe the Apoſtacy of the next Parents takes off the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41503:31"/> federal holineſs of their Seed; as we ſee in the poſterity of <hi>Iſmael</hi> and <hi>Eſau.</hi> 3. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if Infants ſhould have this right in their Grand-fathers, where ſhall we ſtop? ſhall it be extended to a thouſand Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as ſome miſ-apply that promiſe in <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.6. That cannot be true: for then the Children of the Jews; and Turks, and Heathen, all the world over, have a right to Bapiſm, in ſome of their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors within that time, contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Coral∣lary. </seg>5</label> Then Church-covenant is no formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble matter, but deſirable. Is it a yoke? 1. It is Chriſts yoke, which is eaſie, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29, 30. he will make it eaſie. Depend upon his faithfulneſs, as Surety of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, for ability to be faithful in your diſcharge of your Covenant with the Church. 2. It is not a yoke of bondage, but of precious liberties; whereby you have right in all the outward priviledges of the Goſpel. 3. Nor is Church-fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip a priſon, but, if God call, they muſt conſent to your remove from them, and follow you with their prayers. It is, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, a ſtrong but ſweet ingagement of all upright-hearted Chriſtians to pleaſe <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to be to his honour, in that ſtate. So doth the Marriage-covenant oblige thoſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41503:31"/> that are in that ſtate, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.34. &amp; 11.7. From whence, the Apoſtle argueth for the like care in particular Churches, and the Members of them, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.24. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.23. which alſo was a ſpecial end and uſe of the Covenant, wherein <hi>Abraham</hi> and the Church of the Jews ſtood bound unto God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1, 2. and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.31, 32. and the contrary diſcovered the inſincerity and hypocriſie of others, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.37. In like manner it bindeth the Members of the Church to all the duties of their Church-relation mutually, both Officers and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and quickneth them thereunto, through the influence and aſſiſtance of Chriſt the head of the Church, by his Spirit in them all; <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.15, 16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. to 28. And therefore I cannot but wonder, that ſome, who do approve and plead for all other Covenants, <hi>viz.</hi> Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal, Conjugal, Social Covenants, ſhould yet diſlike, and oppoſe Church-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Coral∣lary. </seg>6</label> From the premiſes we may ſee when the Church-Covenant is broken, and how great their ſin is, who do ſcandalouſly and contumaciouſly perſiſt therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:41503:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Concerning the quantity and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of a Chriſtian Church.</head>
               <p>THE Church, which Chriſt calls his Church, he telleth <hi>Peter,</hi> that he will build it; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Rock</hi> (Mat. 16.18.) <hi>I will build my Church.</hi> Where, the verb is in the firſt perſon, and in the future tenſe. 1. He ſpeaketh in the firſt Perſon, not in the ſecond, to ſhew, that though he will uſe men, as his inſtruments, in this work, yet it is his preſence and bleſſing that cauſeth the work to proſper in their hands, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9. It is by the Spirit of the Lord that Church-work is carried on ſuccesfully, <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.6. 2.<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Bradf.</hi> Anſw. to the Arch. B. of <hi>York</hi> in Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> his Act &amp; Mon. in a Conference between them and the Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> in the Compter in <hi>Breadſtreet.</hi>
                  </note> He ſpeaketh in the future tenſe, not in the praeter, or preſent; for, though Chriſt was in all ages the builder of the Church, yet he thus ſpeaketh of the Church under the New Teſtament, becauſe it was to be conſtituted after his Death, Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41503:32"/> and Aſcenſion, when the Goſpel ſhould ſhine forth ſo clearly, that it ſhould ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure the light of former ages, as the Sun riſing in its ſtrength, doth the light of the Stars: and it ſhould <hi>appear,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 2.11.</note> 
                  <hi>bringing Salvation to all men,</hi> even to the Gentiles, and they ſhould be gathered and joyned unto Chriſt, that <hi>one Head,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Eph. 1.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ. 3.6. &amp; 2.13, 14</note> and <hi>become Members of his Body, together with the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Jews,</hi> in Church-communion viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, <hi>the partition Wall being broken down.</hi> And, becauſe all Nations could not be joyned together in one viſible Church (as the Nation of the Jews might be, and was) to have their ſolemn ſet meetings together, to worſhip God thrice a year, or once in an age; the Lord Jeſus inſtitut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Congregational-Church among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and inveſted every ſuch Church with ſufficient Church-power within it ſelf, for attainment of all the ends of Church-communion. This is the Church, which Chriſt ſaith, he will build, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriates it to himſelf, <hi>My Church,</hi> 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is his Inſtitution. 2. Becauſe his Name is called and put upon it. The Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it are, not <hi>Moſes</hi> his diſciples, but Chriſts, and therefore were, of old, called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> Act. 11.26.</p>
               <p>This title of <hi>Church,</hi> though it be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41503:33"/> ſome times to a civil Aſſembly, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.41. yet ſo it is not taken in this place. For Chriſt no where calleth a civil Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, his Church. Therefore it muſt ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie an holy Society. And in that ſenſe, the Scripture applieth this title ſundry wayes. 1. To Godly Families, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.5. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. where the Church, in ſuch an houſe, is diſtinguiſhed from the Congregational Church. For <hi>Paul</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to the Congregational Aſſembly to ſalute <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> and the Church in their houſe. Their houſe, it ſeemeth, conſiſted (all) of Godly perſons, in <hi>Pauls</hi> judgement; elſe, he would have ſaid, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute them of ſuch an houſe, who are in the Lord: and it was an exemplary Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and a ſeminary of the Church, yet not ſuch a Church as was capable of all Church Officers, and power, as this, meant in the text, hath by the gift of Chriſt. 2. Sometimes it ſignifieth the Catholick viſible Church, <hi>Heb,</hi> 12.23. but that hath been from the beginning, and doth not, nor can meet in one place, on earth to worſhip God. Therefore it is not meant here. 3. Moſt commonly, it ſignifieth a Congregational Church, or, an holy So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety joyned together by an holy Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, in one Congregation, to walk toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41503:33"/> according to all the Ordinances and Lawes given by Chriſt to his Church. And ſo ſometimes it ſignifieth a definite particular Congregation, meeting toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one place, for the publick wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and their mutual edification: as that at <hi>Corinth,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.18, 20. and 14.23. And in that acceptation, it notes, ſometimes the Brethren, as diſtinguiſhed from the Elders; <hi>Act.</hi> 15.22. Sometimes the Elders and Brethren aſſembled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20. but never, the Elders meeting apart from the Brethren. But, in this place it doth not ſignifie a particular definite Church. For there is no particular Chriſtian Church built by Chriſt more, or rather, than other. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth, that Chriſt ſpeaks of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Congregational Church here, in an indefinite ſenſe. And ſo, the word Church is applyed in the New Teſtament, when <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, he perſecuted the Church, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.6. Not, that at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> only, or <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> but all the Churches in Judea, <hi>Gal..</hi> 1.22, 23. In this ſenſe, Chriſt calls every Chriſtian Congregational Church, thus built, his Church.</p>
               <p>From the words thus opened, this doctrinal concluſion is to be collect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <hi>viz.</hi> That it is the will and appointment
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41503:34"/> of Jeſus Chriſt, that the Chriſtian Church, under the New Teſtament, be, in reſpect of its quantity and compaſs, Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>4</label> This we ſhall endeavour to prove, both by Scripture and Reaſon. 1. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in the writings of the Apoſtles, clearly ſheweth, that they ſo underſtood this branch of the Church-Charter, and therefore they ſpeak of Chriſtian-Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as ſeveral and diſtinct from one another, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. and 14.33. Yea, in one and the ſame Country, as <hi>Galatia, Gal,</hi> 1.2. <hi>Judea, v.</hi> 22. <hi>Macedonia.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.1. Yea in <hi>Corinth,</hi> where God had much people, <hi>Act.</hi> 18.10. yet the Church there was but one Congregation, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. and, though <hi>Cenchrea</hi> was a Port near unto <hi>Corinth,</hi> yet it had a Church diſtinct from <hi>Corinth; Rom.</hi> 16.1. The Church alſo in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> though a greater number of Believers was declared to be there, than we read of in other Cities, yet it was but one Congregation; <hi>Act.</hi> 2.41, 44, 47. and 6.2, 15. The ſame holdeth concerning o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great Cities; the Church, in every one of them, was Congregational: and, if the number of Believers grew too great for one Congregation, doubtleſs more Churches were gathered in ſuch a place
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41503:34"/> and caſe: &amp; if ſeveral parts of the Church met in times of Perſecution, now and then, here and there, as they might; yet they continued one Congregation, having the ſame Officers, in common, for any thing appears in Scripture to the contrary. Now let us ſee, why the Chriſtian Church muſt be Congregational.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> The firſt Reaſon is from the end of Church-fellowſhip, which is mutual edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, in the uſe of the means inſtituted by Chriſt thereunto. <hi>Let all things be done unto edification,</hi> 1. Cor. 14.26. but how can this be attained, unleſs they ſo meet together, <hi>that all may learn, and all may be comforted. v.</hi> 13? Hence all the Members of the Church are exhorted, not to <hi>forſake their aſſembling together, Heb.</hi> 10.25. which was the praiſe of the primitive Church in <hi>Jeruſalem, Act.</hi> 2.42, 44. Therefore a particular viſible Church is compared to a flock, which are fed together, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28; and to an Houſe or Family, the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers whereof injoy the ſame Family-pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges in common, under the ſame fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-order; 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> The ſecond Reaſon is, from their duty to take up offences among Brethren, which cannot be ended privately, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17, 18. which implyeth two things. 1. That the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41503:35"/> Church muſt conſiſt of more than <hi>two or three:</hi> for though <hi>two or three</hi> may watch over one another, admoniſh one another; and, in caſe of obſtinancy, withdraw from a convicted delinquent: and, though <hi>two or three</hi> praying together, may expect the preſence and bleſſing of Chriſt, as <hi>v.</hi> 19, 20. upon their admonition; yet <hi>two or three</hi> cannot iſſue the matter compleatly, in way of Church-cenſure, but muſt <hi>tell the Church:</hi> Therefore the Church muſt neceſſarily conſiſt of a greater number. Again, how can <hi>two or three</hi> chooſe the four ſorts of Officers amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which are deſcribed by four living creatures, in <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.6, 7. <hi>viz.</hi> Paſtor, Teacher, Ruling Elder, and Deacon? 2. That they muſt not exceed the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and compaſs of one Congregation. For the Church muſt meet ordinarily together with their Officers, for theſe purpoſes. Therefore the Scripture ſheweth that the whole Church did meet together to chuſe and ordain Officers, as Deacons, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.2, 3, 5. Elders; <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. to receive and admit Members, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.26. for Propheſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.23. for the Seals, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20. and for Cenſures, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4. and to releaſe from cenſures. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6, 7. So much for proof of the point. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ctaries are theſe.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:41503:35"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Coroll. </seg>1</label> Then the Congregational frame of a Chriſtian Church is no humane inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or conſtitution. True it is, that the Pariſh frame, as it was wont to joyn all the inhabitants within ſuch a praecinct, into one Church, injoyning them all to communicate at the Lords Table, at leaſt at Eaſter, is meerly humane, not being meaſured by the Golden Reed, which is the Church-meaſure, but by the Court-meaſure, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1, 2. But that Members ſo qualified as Chriſt requireth, and ſo confederating, ſhould ordinarily meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gather in one Congregation, for the ſolemn worſhip of God, and their mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al edification, is the Ordinance of Chriſt, and according to the meaſure of the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Reed, whereby the City and Gates, and the dimenſions of the New-Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem are meaſured, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.15. that they ſhall not be ſo few, as to cut off Church-juriſdiction within themſelves; nor ſo many, but that all may hear and be edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and be governed by the Power, which Chriſt hath given to the Church to preſerve the purity of his Worſhip, and of their fellowſhip within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Coroll. </seg>2</label> Then, when a People grow to be ſo numerous in any Church, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41503:36"/> ordinarily meet together, to Church-ends; it is the mind of Chriſt, that they ſhould be diſtributed into ſundry Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational Churches. For, though many thouſands of Iſrael met together in the court of the Temple at Jeruſalem to offer Sacrifice; becauſe they might ſtand in ſo large a place together and ſee the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices burnt; yet that will not prove, that ſuch multitudes ſhould be Members of a Chriſtian Church, where more communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is required, then in ſeeing ſome one Ordinance performed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Coroll. </seg>3</label> Then, it is not arbitrary, but a duty for every Chriſtian, to endeavour to joyn himſelf in Memberſhip with a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional inſtituted Church of Chriſt: who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever have opportunity, and neglect ſo to do, they greatly ſin againſt God, and break the ſecond Commandment, in not worſhiping him according to his inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and alſo againſt their own ſouls, in depriving themſelves of the bleſſing, which he hath annexed unto his Inſtitution; <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.24. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. and if they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in that neglect, they can hardly be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Believers truly ſeeking the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, what profeſſion of Religion ſoever they make otherwiſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33. and they ſin againſt their poſterity alſo,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41503:36"/> to whom God promiſeth mercy, upon their parents worſhipping him according to his Inſtitutions: If the Lord doth good to the poſterity of ſuch, it is meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from his own good pleaſure, but not from their Parents Covenant, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.61.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Concerning the Churches impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſtability.</head>
               <p>TO the Church built by Chriſt upon this Rock, he hath promiſed and given this great priviledge, <hi>that the gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it.</hi>] <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in the Scripture, ſignifieth, not Hell, but the ſtate of the dead, or the Grave, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> are enemies van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed by Chriſt for his Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.26, 55. and ſhalbe caſt into the lake of fire, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.14. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> are the <hi>gates of Death,</hi> in <hi>Job.</hi> 38.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.18. <hi>and the gates of the Grave,</hi> Iſa. 38.10. <hi>i. e.</hi> the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Death and the Grave, which ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth on them, as a Serjeant, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.3. The ſum is; Let the Church be brought to the loweſt, that it ſeems to be dead,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41503:37"/> as thoſe two Witneſſes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8, 9. and buried, as Chriſt's natural body was, for a time; yet neither Death, nor the Grave ſhall prevail agaiſt it. Yet we muſt not limit the ſenſe of theſe words, only to the power of Death and the Grave, but it muſt be extended to all Satans plots and aſſaults againſt the Church, againſt which if Chriſt did not help them, Death and the Grave would prevail againſt them, to their eternal deſtruction. We conclude therefore, that, in this Text, by <hi>the gates of Hell,</hi> are meant, all the machinations of Satan, and temptations whatſoever, whereby he laboureth to hinder the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſts Church, to draw thoſe from Chriſt, who are built upon him. <hi>The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing</hi> of them ſignifies their effectual working unto the attainment of thoſe ends. The ſum is, a promiſe that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, with all his policies and powers, ſhall neither hinder the building of Chriſts Church, nor cauſe the Church thus built to apoſtatize from Chriſt. And that this is the true ſenſe and meaning of the words, whatſoever Socinians, or Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſay to the contrary, may thus be evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: 1. Becauſe the thing promiſed, is the diſabling of what ever oppoſeth the building of the Church upon this Rock,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41503:37"/> or its conſtant adhering to Chriſt, from prevailing to thoſe ends: but ſo do Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan's temptations; Therefore they are meant by the gates of Hell. 2. Becauſe whatſoever goeth forth out of the gates of Hell, or hath its beginning from thence, is meant in this phraſe: but the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and Machinations of Satan, by himſelf and his inſtruments, Hereticks and Tyrants, go forth thence; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are meant in this phraiſe. 3. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Peter,</hi> to whom Chriſt ſpake theſe words, deſcribes unbelievers, the adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of this building, as belonging to the gates of Hell; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7, 8. 4. Becauſe the proportion, which Chriſt implyes, in theſe words, requireth that they be ſo under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. The proportion is between two Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that of Heaven, which hath its gates, and keyes, in <hi>v.</hi> 19. and the other of Hell, which hath its gates; whence it endeavors the ruine and overthrow of that, but ſhall not prevail. Seeing therefore City is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to City, and Gates to Gates, and one (<hi>viz.</hi> the Church) is conſidered in the ſtate of preſent building; it is moſt ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that the other be alſo looked at, as it oppoſeth that, in the preſent, whilſt it is militant upon earth. But from hence, that Chriſt promiſeth that the gates of Hell
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41503:38"/> ſhall not prevail againſt his Church thus built, ſome infer, that Chriſt meaneth only <hi>the inviſible Catholick Church:</hi> For that only, ſay they, is bulilt on this Rock, and only that ſhall not fail. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It is true, that the Catholick inviſible Church is built upon Chriſt, by effectual and unfeigned Faith, and that ſhall not fail: For that is <hi>the general Aſſembly, and Church of the fiſt-born, which are enrolled in Heaven,</hi> Heb. 12.23. And all the gates of Hell cannot prevail againſt thoſe that are written in Heaven. 2. But it is not true, that theſe only are built on this Rock. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, that a particular viſible Church, rightly conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as that at <hi>Corinth,</hi> is built upon this Rock, or Rocky-foundation, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10, 11. and being ſo built, is under the ſpecial protection of God in Chriſt; in reſpect whereof the Lord promiſeth any ſuch Church, as well among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as the <hi>Jews, Whoſoever ſhall gather himſelf</hi> againſt thee, ſhall fall, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.15. and <hi>all the weapons that are made againſt thee ſhall not proſper,</hi> verſ. 17. And it is clear, that Chriſt, in this place, ſpeaks of ſuch a Church as is built upon the confeſſion of Faith, ſuch as <hi>Peter</hi> made, viſibly and publickly; whereupon, not the inviſible
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41503:38"/> Catholick Church, but viſible particular Churches are built: Therefore theſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are meant here.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>5</label> The Church of Chriſt, built by himſelf upon this Rock, in uſing the means which he hath appointed for their ſafety, is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable. The Church of Chriſt is here indefinitely taken, for a particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational-Church inſtituted by Chriſt, according to the ſenſe of the former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions, not, for this or that, defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely.</p>
               <p>Therefore if any object, that the gates of Hell have prevailed againſt the Greek-Churches, thoſe <hi>golden Candleſticks</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and againſt <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe <hi>Faith was ſpoken of throughout the whole World,</hi> and againſt ſundry other particular Churches?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I <hi>Anſwer,</hi> 1. Though it be true, that the gates of Hell have prevailed againſt this or that particular Church; yet not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a particular Church, indefinitly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, or (which is the ſame) againſt the Church, in general, exiſting in its particulars. In this ſenſe, the viſible Church doth not fail. For, (1.) Chriſt ever had, and will have ſome or other viſible Church on Earth, wherein the general nature of a viſible Church is preſerved, as the <hi>Genus</hi> is in its <hi>Species,</hi> and the nature
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41503:39"/> of man in this or that individual; as when the Lord preſerved <hi>Noah</hi> and his Family, in the Ark, mankind was preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in them, though multitudes of men were deſtroyed in the Deluge. (2.) Chriſt will ſhew, that he makes a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Churches, wherein are ſome true Believers mixed with many Hypocrites, and other Societies. Therefore he will not ſuffer ſuch viſible Churches to be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally deſtroyed, as he doth his open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.8, 9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.8, 9. &amp; 6.13. 2. Though it be true, that the Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> have been prevailed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt by the gates of Hell, yet not, as they were built by Chriſt, or planted by the Apolſtes, but their degenerate Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Succeſſours, who were not built on this Rock, but on an outward Form, and neglected the means appointed by Chriſt for their ſafety. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> forewarned the <hi>Romans</hi> to beware of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, by the example of the <hi>Jews,</hi> Rom. 11.12. They, nevertheleſs, in ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing generations, did degenerate from the Faith and Profeſſion of their Predeceſſors, and ſo fell into the gulf of <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Apoſtacy. But, as when God took his viſible Kingdom from the <hi>Jews,</hi> for their obſtinacy in unbelief, he did not deſtroy
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:41503:39"/> his viſible Kingdom totally from the face of the Earth, but <hi>gave it to a Nation bringing forth the fruits thereof, Mat.</hi> 21.43. So, though, in his righteous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt Apoſtates, he may deſtroy this, or that particular Congregational Church; yet the <hi>gates of Hell</hi> ſhall not prevail wholly againſt the Church-ſtate, but it ſhall be preſerved. He doth but tranſlate the Candleſtick, not break it all to pieces; he doth but remove it out of one place into another, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.5. and ſtill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth it, in ſome particular Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or other. 3. Though the gates of Hell have ſometime, and in ſome degree, prevailed againſt this or that particular viſible Church, <hi>holding faſt the profeſſion of their Faith without wavering;</hi> yet they have not prevailed according to the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of theſe words. They have prevailed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, only in ſome reſpect; as, 1. in Temporals, to impoveriſh them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. to bring them under bondage, as <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> did the Iſraelites; to eſtabliſh a decree for their deſtruction, as <hi>Haman</hi> did againſt the Jews; to put multitudes of them to death, as the ten perſecuting Emperors did the Chriſtians, and as the high Prieſt and the Jews dealt with Chriſt. 2. In Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals, 1. to ſcatter the Members of the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:41503:40"/> Church; ſo far the gates of Hell prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt them, upon occaſion of <hi>Stephen,</hi> Act. 8.1. and to cauſe the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to flye into the Wilderneſs, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 2. To aſſault them with temptations; as Chriſt told <hi>Peter,</hi> that Satan had deſired <hi>to winnow him like Wheat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But they could not prevail againſt the Church, <hi>abſolutely and totally.</hi> 1. Not againſt all of them in <hi>Smyrna,</hi> by outward calamities, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. Nor againſt all in <hi>Sardis,</hi> by temptation, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.4. 2. Nor totally againſt the whole Church. For God did raiſe up unexpected helps; for the Woman fled into the Wilderneſs, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.6, 14, 16. to that part of them, which remains on earth; and, for the other part of them, God will receive his people, when outward ſubſiſtence fails, into everlaſting habitations, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.9. And, when the gates of Hell prevail, to the diſperſion of a particular Church built on this Rock, yet that is not to their deſtruction, but tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the multiplication, and inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of particular Churches. The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſion of the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> was like the diſperſion of Seed into the Field, which bringeth forth a more plentiful Harveſt; ſo, their diſperſion prevailed againſt the gates of Hell, to the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:41503:40"/> of ſundry Churches, <hi>Act.</hi> 11.19, 21. Thus the Lord turned the Policies of the gates of Hell againſt themſelves, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that promiſe, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.3. Thus we ſee the impregnable ſtability of Chriſt his Church built upon this Rock.</p>
               <p>We ſhall now prove by Reaſon, that it muſt be ſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> From Chriſt, who is the Head of the viſible Church, as well as of the inviſible, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.27. And he will not ſuffer the ſound Members of his Body to be plucked and torn from it by the gates of Hell. He is the builder of his Chuch, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.3, 4. and therefore will eſtabliſh it. When the Ark was built by <hi>Noah,</hi> as Gods Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, according to God's appointment, it ſtood againſt all the power of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge. He is the Foundation, as he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lived, and publickly confeſſed, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he buildeth his Church. Againſt an Houſe ſo built, the Winds and Waves cannot prevail, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.24, 25.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> From the Promiſes given to ſuch a Church, which are of two ſorts. 1. For protection, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.5, 6. where be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſieth concerning the Church of Chriſt under the New Teſtament, and deſcribes Gods protection over them, by a twofold alluſion; 1. By the Pillar of Cloud and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:41503:41"/> Fire that protected the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> at the Red Sea, from <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt. 2. By the covering of the Tabernacle, and the holy things in it from all injuries of weather, <hi>Exod.</hi> 26.14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.16. And his power is ingaged to perform his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.28, 29. And his Providence will order all iſſues and events thereunto, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.16, 17. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18, 20. 2ly. For vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20. If the Lord will tread Satan under their feet, he will ſee to it that Satan ſhall not tread them under his feet.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> From the titles given to particular vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Churches. They are frequently, in the New Teſtament, called the Kingdom of Heaven; and Hell cannot prevail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Heaven. They are called the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt, and God the Father hath eſtabliſhed his Kingdom by an oath, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.35, 36. To confirm our Faith herein, he calls the Sun and Moon to be witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>verſ.</hi> 37. The Sun may be clouded ſometimes, and Moon is ſometimes in the Full, ſometimes in the Wane, but ſtill it is in the Heaven: So it is with the Church on Earth.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Whitt. ad Rat. Camp. Reſp. p. <hi>56.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Semper &amp; fuiſſe in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, &amp; futuram deinceps Eccleſiam, non du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitamus: quanquam ejus aſpectum aliquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do illuſtrem ut conſpici ab omnibus poſſit,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:41503:41"/> aliquando tantâ caligine, ut vix agnoſcas, obſcuratam eſſe fateamur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And it belongs to Chriſt, to break the Serpent's Head; who can proceed no further than to bruiſe his h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. He is that little ſtone that brake the Image to pieces, which repreſented the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies and Powers, whereby the gates of Hell ſought to prevail againſt Chriſt and his Church, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.45. Chriſts Church is called an Houſe of prayer to all Nations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.7. The Iſrael of God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. in alluſion to the change of <hi>Jacobs</hi> name, who by prayer obtained victory and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection againſt <hi>Eſau, Gen.</hi> 32.28. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.2, 3. So ſhall the Church of Chriſt, by pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, obtain deliverance from the gates of Hell, that they ſhall not prevail againſt them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> From the ſtate of the Devils themſelves, and all their inſtruments. 1. They are curſed. <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.3. <hi>I will curſe them that curſe thee,</hi> therefore they ſhall not proſper in their interprizes againſt the Church of Chriſt. 2. They were conquered, and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated, and triumphed over by Chriſt, before he did build his Church, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8, 12. Therefore ſhall not hinder the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it, nor deſtroy it being built. 3. They are enemies unto Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41503:42"/> Therefore ſhall not prevail. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2.2, 3, 4. and, 110.1, 2. Let us briefly note ſome Corollaries hence.</p>
               <p>Then in vain boaſteth that Roman Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, of the infallibility of their Popes, as <hi>Peter's</hi> ſucceſſors, and of the indefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of their Church, as built upon <hi>Peter;</hi> when as, neither had <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf any ſuch priviledge, as to be infallible. The next ſtory in this 16th of <hi>Matthew</hi> evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the contrary, <hi>v.</hi> 23. Nor, by <hi>the Rock,</hi> whereupon Chriſt builds his Church, is meant the perſon of <hi>Peter,</hi> or <hi>Peter's</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion perſonally, as it had relation to him, but as it is conſidered really in it ſelf, and is common to all the Diſciples, and to all viſible Believers, which may be thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed: 1. Becauſe <hi>Peters</hi> confeſſion muſt have relation to the matter which he confeſſed. But <hi>Peter</hi> confeſſed not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>Thou art the Chriſt, the Son of the living God;</hi> Therefore his <hi>confeſſion</hi> had relation to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> not to himſelf. 2. Becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> confeſſed no more than that which he knew the other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples believed before he ſpeake: For Chriſt's queſtion being general, <hi>What ſay ye? Peter</hi> anſwered, as the mouth of the reſt: but the Apoſtles, before he ſpeak, believed <hi>Chriſt confeſſed,</hi> and not <hi>Peter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing.</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:41503:42"/> 3. Becauſe, this <hi>Rock,</hi> is that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion whereupon Chriſt ſaith he will build his Church: But whoſoever ſhall truly believe that which <hi>Peter</hi> confeſſed, <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt the Son of the living God, and confeſs or profeſs it, in due order, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly <hi>built on this Rock,</hi> though he had never heard of <hi>Peter's</hi> name. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the confeſſion, rightly underſtood, had relation unto Chriſt, and not to the perſon of <hi>Peter.</hi> 4. Becauſe the Rock ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth that which is immoveable and impregnable, ſuch as is Chriſt and his truth: But <hi>Peter's</hi> confeſſion was mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and ſhaken, at one time, thrice deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this confeſſion of his Lord. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this confeſſion, which Chriſt calls the Rock, had not relation to <hi>Peter,</hi> but only to Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Coroll. </seg>2</label> Then they that would have a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church to be impregnable, ſtable, and firm againſt the prevailing of the gates of Hell, muſt ſee that it be built upon this Rock, and not upon humane formes. 1. That Chriſt himſelf be the builder of it, according to his own inſtitutions, not the policies or cuſtoms of men. 2.<note n="*" place="margin">Ex quo patet, quòd Eccleſia, non conſiſtit in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus, ratione poteſtatis vel dignitatis Eccleſiaſticae, vel ſaecularis &amp;c. ſed in illis perſonis, in quibus eſt notitia vera, &amp; confeſſio fidei &amp; veritatis. <hi>Lyra in loc.</hi>
                  </note> That the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:41503:43"/> materials, of which it conſiſts, be ſuch, as believe and profeſs their Faith in Chriſt publickly before the Lord, and his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. 3. That they be firmly joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in one Congregation, by an holy Covenant of ſubjection and ſubmiſſion to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to one another in him, and accordingly walk together in obedience to Chriſt, and his Rules, reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Satan in all his Temptations and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations, through Chriſt ſtrengthning them, without whom they can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.5. and that they improve carefully and faithfully the power, which Chriſt hath given them, <hi>viz. the Keyes of the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> in opening and ſhutting, binding and looſing, according to Chriſt his appointment, for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of his Church ſafe in the purity of their Faith and Order, againſt <hi>the gates of Hell,</hi> which is the next thing to be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:41503:43"/>
            <head>The Second Part.</head>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Concerning the power given of Chriſt unto ſuch a Church, as the firſt and proper ſubject of it.</head>
               <p>THe ſecond branch or part of the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is, concerning the Power given by Chriſt unto ſuch Churches, to have and uſe all the means appointed by him for their eſtabliſhment againſt the the gates of Hell, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.19. <hi>And I will give unto thee the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven; and whatſoever thou ſhalt bind on Earth, ſhall be bound in Heaven; and whatſoever thou ſhalt looſe on Earth, ſhall be looſed in Heaven.</hi> Theſe words contain, 1. A grant of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. 2. A ratification of that Grant. We ſhall ſpeak to them diſtinctly. 1. To Chriſt his grant of Power; and therein, 1. Explicate the terms, by ſhewing, what is meant, 1 by <hi>the Kingdom of Heaven;</hi> 2. by the <hi>Keys</hi> of it. 3 What this appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priation,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:41503:44"/> or application of them imports, <hi>To thee I will give.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. By <hi>the Kingdom of Heaven</hi>] is meant, both the Kingdom of Grace &amp; Glory; and that the Kingdom of Glory is alſo meant, the following words ſhew, when he ſaith, <hi>What you bind on Earth, is bound in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> &amp;c. 2. By the Keys (which are a ſign of Power, and are put, by a Metoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, for the Subject, the Power it ſelf) is meant, Church-power; which is either Supreme, and Soveraign, in Chriſt only, as Lord and Head of his Church, who alone hath the Key of <hi>David, which openeth, and no man ſhutteth, and ſhutteth and no man openeth;</hi> in <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.7. or ſubordinate and delegate, ſuch as is in Chriſt's Stewards. This is noted, by <hi>Keys,</hi> in the Plural num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, in this place, which ſignifie all pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er delegated from Chriſt, to diſpenſe and adminiſter all the holy things of his Houſe, according to Chriſt's will, and in the order preſcribed by him to that end. For all power, wherewith the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus betruſteth his Church, aims at this which is here expreſſed, <hi>to open, and ſhut, to bind, and looſe.</hi> 3. <hi>To thee I will give</hi>] The Application of this Grant is to <hi>Peter,</hi> in the name of the Church, which Chriſt promiſed to build upon himſelf, believed
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:41503:44"/> on, and publickly profeſſed, as <hi>Peter</hi> did before him, and his fellow-Diſciples in Chriſts School, at this time. And the promiſe is more fitly given to <hi>Peter,</hi> in the name of the Church, than to the Church by name, becauſe it was not the Church that made this confeſſion, but <hi>Peter</hi> in the name of the Church. But here we muſt make a little ſtand, to examine the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry claims which have been made to this Right, upon ſeveral pretences from this Text. 1. Some, looking at <hi>Peter,</hi> as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the Catholick viſible-Church, conceive that a <hi>general Council</hi> (which, they ſay, is the Catholick Church, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatively) is the Church here meant, to which Chriſt gives <hi>the Keys of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven.</hi> But that cannot be. For particular viſible Churches, in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles dayes, had, and exerciſed, the Keyes compleatly within themſelves; yet was there no general Council, till the time of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> which was three hundred years after Chriſt. 2. Others look at this Grant, as peculiar to <hi>Peter,</hi> conſidered, as the Prince and chief of the Apoſtles, and to the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> as his ſucceſſors. But this <hi>Papal</hi> uſurpation, the Councils of <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Baſil</hi> ſtrongly and juſtly oppoſed, ſhewing, that the Keys, which
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:41503:45"/> are here given to <hi>Peter,</hi> are, in <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.21, 22, 23. given to all the Apoſtles, and that <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf is enjoyned in <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. to tell the Church. 3. Others think, that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, conſidered, not repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, but in it ſelf, is the firſt ſubject of the Keys: Yet theſe differ among themſelves. For ſome affirm it of the inviſible, others of the viſible Catholick Church. As for the terms; we know, that <hi>viſible</hi> &amp; <hi>inviſible,</hi> do not note diſtinct <hi>ſpecies</hi> or <hi>kindes</hi> of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but are only ſeveral adjuncts of the ſame Church, which is called <hi>inviſible,</hi> in reſpect of the inward and inviſible union, which Members have with Chriſt the Head, by the Spirit and Faith; and <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible,</hi> in reſpect of their outward Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their Faith, which is viſible to men. But in neither of theſe ſenſes, is the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church the firſt ſubject of the Keys. 1. Not <hi>as inviſible;</hi> for that is not built by a viſible profeſſion, ſuch as <hi>Peter's</hi> was; nor are the Ordinances diſpenſed or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred viſibly in it, to, or by men in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible fellowſhip. Add hereunto, that the Keys here given to <hi>Peter,</hi> can ſhut out of the Kingdom of Heaven, even the ſame perſons, to whom they have opened the door before; which cannot befal Believers in the viſible Church.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:41503:45"/>2. Not <hi>as viſible.</hi> For the Scripture doth not acknowledge a Catholick viſible Church. The Catholick Church is not viſible, as a Church, and the Church that is viſible is not Catholick. Though the Catholick Church may be viſible in its ſingular Members; yet ſo, they are not a Church: or, though it may be viſible in particular Congregations;<note place="margin">See <hi>Mr. Cott.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the way of Congreg. Churches, par. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>56</hi>
                  </note> yet none of them is Catholick: or, though all of them, if they could meet together, may be called a Catholick Church, or general Aſſembly; yet ſo, it cannot be the firſt ſubject of the Keys, <hi>i. e.</hi> of all Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal power: for ſuch Aſſemblies,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See Mr.</hi> Hooker<hi>'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Survey, part</hi> 1. <hi>ch.</hi> 14 &amp; 15.</note> if poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, are extraordinary: and extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Aſſemblies are not fit Judicatories, to hear and cenſure ordinary offences, or to adminiſter the ordinary acts of Church-power. 2. If the viſible Catholick Church be conſidered, <hi>as totum integrale,</hi> which is ſuch a whole as ariſeth out of the ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of all particular Churches (as an Army is made up of all the ſeveral Regiments and Troops, or a Kingdom of all the Cities and Counties within it) it cannot be the firſt ſubject of the Keyes, <hi>i. e.</hi> of all Church-power. For, 1. parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches are the Members, which give the eſſential cauſes, whence the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of this whole is made up; and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:41503:46"/> therefore, in nature, before it, as the cauſe is before its effect. 2. Church-Officers, with their Offices, are ſet ordinarily, by Chriſts Inſtitution, only in ſuch a Church, where they are called the Choſen; but that is a particular Church; <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. For that choice and calling is the foundation of the relation between Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and People, and of the duties both of the Rulers, and of the Ruled, mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. 3. If a Catholick integral Church ariſeth from all particular Churches, as Members of it, joyned together; then it muſt be diſtinct from them all, as the whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is a thing diſtinct from its ſeveral Members, then alſo there muſt be ſome Officer, and Ordinance, and Act be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to it, which doth not apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to particular Churches; as there is a General over an Army, beſides the Captains and Officers of the ſeveral Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments; and a Supreme Monarch in a Kingdom, beſides the Governors in the ſeveral Corporations, and Counties: But no ſuch Catholick-Church, diſtinct from all particular Churches, can be ſhewen, nor Officers, or acts of it, beſides thoſe which are exerciſed in particular Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. 4. Dioceſan Biſhops look at theſe words, as giving the Keys to them, as the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:41503:46"/> Succeſſors of the Apoſtles, whence they aſſume the power of Ordinathon and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, as belonging to them, <hi>jure divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no.</hi> A claim, which King <hi>James,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of his policy (which he called his King-craft) or out of his inſight into the Scripture, would not ſuffer them to pretend, in his time. Nor indeed is there any warrant for it in Scripture, as it hath been abundantly proved by ſundry wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes againſt that uſurpation. We read of Biſhops in the New-Teſtament, but what? Not one Biſhop over many Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but many Biſhops over one Church; not Dioceſan, but Congregational Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. Thoſe whom <hi>Luke</hi> calls Elders, in <hi>Act.</hi> 20.17. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth Biſhops, in <hi>v.</hi> 28. The Biſhops which the Apoſtles acknowledge to be Chriſts Ordinance, to continue in the Chriſtian Church, are Congregational Elders, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1-8. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5, 7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1, 2. and all the Teaching-Elders are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>fellow-Elders,</hi> coequal in authority, above whom <hi>Paul</hi> acknowledgeth no Rulers in the Church, but rather ſets theſe above all, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17.<note place="margin">Euſeb. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. hiſt. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>43.</hi> Cypr. Ep. l. <hi>3.</hi> Ep. <hi>10</hi> &amp; l. <hi>1.</hi> ep. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> And, when, after the Apoſtles time, one of the Paſtors was called Biſhop, by way of eminency, for orders ſake; yet, for many years, he did no act of power, but, 1. with
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:41503:47"/> conſent of the Presbytery; 2. with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Cudw.</hi> on the Poſtſcript to <hi>Galat.</hi>
                  </note> and in the preſence, of the People. What is pleaded from <hi>Titus</hi> his ordaining, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. helps not their cauſe: for he did it, as an Evangeliſt, not as a <hi>Dioceſan Prelate;</hi> and the Office of Evangeliſts, together with the Apoſtles, ceaſeth. The Poſtſcript of the ſecond Epiſtle to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> where he is called, <hi>the firſt Biſhop of the Church of the Epheſians;</hi> and of that to <hi>Titus,</hi> where he is called, <hi>the firſt Biſhop of the Church of the Cretians,</hi> are Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phal (as the reſt are) and the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth not with 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. where <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> is called an Evangeliſt, and therefore, not tyed to perſonal reſidence, to abide in one place (as Biſhops and Paſtors are) but the Evangeliſts were to go from place to place, to ſet things in order, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Churches planted by the Apoſtles. The ſame may be ſaid of <hi>Titus.</hi> Nor is the <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> of that Epiſtle of more credit than the former, where the Scribe ſaith, it was written from <hi>Nicopolis. Hiperius</hi> juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſliketh the ground of that opinion in the Scribe, which, he ſaith, was from <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.12. Becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> bade <hi>Titus</hi> come to him to <hi>Nicopolis,</hi> for he <hi>determined to winter there:</hi> whereas, if he were there at that time, he would have ſaid, I purpoſe to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:41503:47"/> winter here, not there; as <hi>Beza</hi> noteth.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Others conclude from this Text, that the power of the Keys. <hi>i. e.</hi> the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Ordination and Eccleſiaſtical Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, is given in <hi>Peter,</hi> to Church-Officers only, eſpecially to Paſtors and Teachers. And that ſuch only, or prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, are meant in this Grant, they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to prove by five reaſons, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally. We will examine them ſeverally, and briefly.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Reaſ. <hi>Becauſe the Keys are given to Stewards by Office.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.12.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The three former Texts ſpeak of the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts Office, and in them, of Paſtors and Teachers, not of Ruling-Elders. But, I ſuppoſe they will not deny the Ruling-Elders to have a Key of Office alſo. The laſt Text proveth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that <hi>the Key</hi> ſometimes ſignifies Office-power given to a Steward, which none deny. But this toucheth not this Text, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. which means not only <hi>Office-Power,</hi> but <hi>all Power,</hi> which ſerves to ſhut and open the Houſe or City of God; not power of the Steward only, but the power of the Spouſe and Wife of this great King, to whom the Lord Chriſt, as her Husband, being gone into a far Country,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:41503:48"/> even to Heaven, hath given power to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit into the Family, and reject, as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhall require, and for thoſe ends, to judge alſo; becauſe ſuch acts require judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to call the Steward to his place, and to put him into it, and to put a Key of Office, by Election, into his hand: and therfore, though all power be not formally in her, yet it cometh originally from her.</p>
               <p>Reaſ. 2. <hi>Becauſe, Chriſt here giveth the Keys only to thoſe, to whom he giveth Official Warrant and Authority, for the actual ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe thereof, in opening and ſhutting, bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and looſing,</hi> i. e. <hi>only to Teachers and Elders.] Anſw.</hi> 1. Though it is true, that Official Warrant and Authority is given only to Teachers &amp; Elders, only Teaching and Ruling Elders have that <hi>formally;</hi> Yet, 2. The power of the Keys is far larger than Office-power, <hi>viz.</hi> to admit, reject, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 3. They have their Office from the Church, and their Office-power, by the Church, originally: Therefore there was power in the Church, before Office-po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, which did communicate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh Office-power to its Officers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Reaſ. <hi>To bind and looſe, are acts of the Office-power of Paſtors, Rulers, Feeders by publick and paſtoral preaching, which doth not belong to Believers.]</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:41503:48"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Binding and looſing, taken in the largeſt ſenſe, as in this Text, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the exerciſe of all the acts of the Keys, or Church-power: and theſe acts are not only by publick and paſtoral preaching (for then, the Ruling-Elder ſhould have no Key to bind or looſe); but alſo by Admonitions, Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Admiſſions, which iſſue from a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of judging, not proper to the Paſtors only, but common to the People with them. 2. Though the Keys be given to the Church; yet ſhe may not exerciſe any act proper to Office-Power, without Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, whom ſhe doth and muſt call to that end, and ſubmit to them in the due ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe thereof.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Reaſ. <hi>If this place give not warrant and authority to Officers, what warrant have they for their Office-Power?]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. This place gives warrant for the People to chooſe their Officers, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Chriſt's appointment, and the Church doth accordingly call them to that place, and inveſt them with Office, with voluntary profeſſed ſubjection to them, in the right exerciſe of that power of Office, which belongs unto them in the Lord. 2. The ſeveral acts of Office-power to be exerciſed by them, are abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:41503:49"/> warranted in other places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Reaſ. <hi>They to whom the Keys are here given, doe authoritatively forgive and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſins, and their Acts are valid in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: but the Church of Believers, wanting Officers, cannot by any warrant of Scripture, authoritatively forgive and retain ſins.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The word, <hi>Authority,</hi> ſometimes is taken more generally, for <hi>Power,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more ſtrictly and properly, for Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Office-Power. In the firſt ſenſe, the Church hath power to foregive judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. in reference to their former cenſure. The Officers forgive au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatively, in the ſecond ſenſe. We proceed to the laſt interpretation.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Others look at the Keys as given to <hi>Peter</hi> here, in the name of a particular viſible Church, indefinitely taken; not of this or that particular definite Church, that all other Churches ſhould receive the Keys from them, or be ſubject to the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the Keyes in their hands: For that will not ſtand with the parity of Churches among themſelves: for, <hi>par in parem non habet imperium.</hi> Therefore the Church, here intended, muſt be taken generally, and indefinitely, as comprehending in it any particular viſible Church, one as well
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:41503:49"/> as another, or the general Church as exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its particulars. If it be objected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this, that <hi>Peter</hi> was not a Member of ſuch a Chriſtian Congregation, when Chriſt ſpake theſe words unto him. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, It is true: for no ſuch Church was then conſtituted. No more was there a Presbytery then conſtituted, when Chriſt directed <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt, in caſe of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate offence obſtinatly perſiſted in, after proceeding in the firſt and ſecond ſtep, to <hi>tell the Church,</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. which yet they hold, but not truly, to be the Presbytery, as we ſhall evince hereafter, with the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of Chriſt. But, in the mean time, all grant that that Rule ſerveth to order Members, how to proceed in ſuch caſes, when particular Churches ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted. And the ſame reaſon is of force in this Text alſo. Some have thought that Chriſt giveth the Keys in this Text, not to the Church of Believers, of which he ſpake in the former verſe, but to the Elders; becauſe he altereth the form of his ſpeech: for, having ſpoken, in the former verſe, of the Church, in the third perſon, ſaying, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Rock I will build my Church, and the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it;</hi> he ſaith not, in this verſe, <hi>and I will give unto it the Keys,</hi> but
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:41503:50"/> varying the perſon, he turneth his ſpeech to <hi>Peter,</hi> ſaying, and <hi>unto thee I will give the Keyes of the Kingdom of Heaven:</hi> but this is a miſtake. Here is no changing of perſon, nor turning of ſpeech, in Chriſt's giving the promiſe of the Keys; but, as Chriſt began, ſo he continueth his ſpeech to <hi>Peter,</hi> upon occaſion of his confeſſion. In <hi>v.</hi> 17. Chriſt pronounceth <hi>Peter bleſſed,</hi> from the cauſe of his confeſſion. In <hi>v.</hi> 18. he giveth a promiſe of reward to <hi>Peters</hi> confeſſion, that, upon this, as upon a Rock, <hi>he will build his Church,</hi> and eſtabliſh it, as impregnable againſt <hi>the gates of Hell.</hi> In <hi>v.</hi> 19. he giveth unto <hi>Peter,</hi> upon occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his publick confeſſion in the name of the Church, a promiſe of <hi>the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Therefore this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is given to the Church, in <hi>Peter,</hi> in ſuch ſort, as, though the uſe of the Keys be various, according to the variety of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings in the Church, yet the power it ſelf of the Keys, is here originally and primarily co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to the<note n="*" place="margin">Toti Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae dedit <hi>Chriſtus</hi> claves, ſed ita, ut in Eccleſiâ certi eſſent qui clavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus utan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ad ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutem Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noremque Dei. <hi>Zanc. in praec. 4. quaeſt. 3.</hi> Vid. <hi>Park.</hi> de Polit. Eccleſ. l. <hi>3</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Church in general,</hi> exiſting in particular Churches. I might produce ſundry Writers, both ancient and modern, of other Countries, and our own, if need required, to confirm this Expoſition (yea, of the Authors quoted by Mr. <hi>P.</hi> not a few conſenting herein;) but I ſhall only
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:41503:50"/> mention <hi>Cyprian</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who, in ſundry places, ſpeak the ſame with us. And theſe two I the rather name, becauſe I find in approved Hiſtories, that ſundry Martyrs, being confirmed in this Truth, by their Teſtimonies, have ſealed it with their blood. <hi>Hieronimus Savanarola,</hi> a Godly learned Preacher in <hi>Florence,</hi> a man endued with a Prophetical Spirit,<note place="margin">Illyr. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. Teſt. verit. cont. <hi>Papam.</hi> p. <hi>565.</hi>
                  </note> was there burnt, for denying the primacy of the Pope, teaching, that the Keys were given, <hi>Eccleſiae toti, non uni Petro,</hi> to the whole Church; and that the Communion ſhould be adminiſtred <hi>ſub utrâque ſpecie,</hi> and againſt humane Traditions, and the Popes indulgencies, and the wicked lives of the Cardinals and Prieſts; and for preaching free Juſtification by Faith in Chriſt, and that the Pope is Antichriſt. This was about the year, 1499. In our own Land, <hi>John Lambert,</hi> in the year,<note place="margin">Fox Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrol. i'th Reign of <hi>Hen. 8th.</hi>
                  </note> 1538, was burnt to death, by the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, himſelf ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in judgement upon him, with all his Nobles and Biſhops, by the wicked counſel of <hi>Stephen Gardiner,</hi> upon 45 Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, whereof this was the 43<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Article, Whether he believed the Pope was Chriſts Vicar, and had power on earth to bind and looſe? He denyed that the Pope was
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:41503:51"/> Chriſts Vicar, and affirmed, that the Keys were given to <hi>Peter,</hi> not for himſelf alone, but in the name of the Church, and prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it out of <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Idem, ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>de ſimplicitate Cleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum,</hi> and <hi>Aug. de Agone Chriſtiano.</hi> Alſo Sir <hi>John Borthwick,</hi> a Scottiſh Knight, in the year 1540, was condemned by the Arch Biſhop of St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> then Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of Scotland, and the Popes Legate, with ſundry Popiſh Biſhops, upon ten Articles, of which this was the firſt, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Popes Supremacy, grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. <hi>To thee will I give the Keys:</hi> which he, from that place, confuted, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming that the Keys were given to the Church in <hi>Peter,</hi> which name was given him upon his confeſſion of Chriſt, in the name of the whole Church; and confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his aſſertion, out of <hi>Cyprian</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine.</hi> So that this is no new, nor ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar expoſition of theſe words, or practice taken up by ſome few of late. Not new; for <hi>Cyprian</hi> wrote about the year 250 af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt; and <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> about the year 410; the laſt of them about 1200 years ſince, and the firſt above 1400 years paſt. I ſhall add hereunto, that, before <hi>Cyprian, Tertullian,</hi> about the year 200, ſhews us, that Church-cenſures were then perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by one particular Church within it
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:41503:51"/> ſelf, and not in any combination of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; <hi>Tertull. Apolog. Cap.</hi> 39. Nor ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar; for ſundry ſorts of Writers, in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Ages and Countries, have conſented therein. I will not enter into that queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (about which there ſeems to be ſome difference in apprehenſions between ſome Godly learned Brethren) Whether the Keys are given to <hi>Peter</hi> under ſeveral con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, as an Apoſtle, and as an El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and as a profeſſing Believer, all being taken joyntly together? or to a ſingle So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, or condition of men, under ſome ſpecial Relation, which ſhare alike in the equality of this Power promiſed unto them? For in the ſubſtance of the matter they agree, 1. That the Keys are promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to <hi>Peter,</hi> in the name of a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional-Church. 2. That this power of the Keys cannot be given to one ſingle Society formally, in all the kinds of it; becauſe it requires ſeveral ſorts of ſubjects for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally different, <hi>viz.</hi> ſome Ruling, ſome Ruled, ſome Teaching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 3. That, til a Congregational-Church be organized, and compleated with all its Officers, it cannot compleatly exerciſe the Keys com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to it. 4. That, nevertheleſs, before it be compleated, it hath power of the Keys, and is the firſt ſubject of them,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:41503:52"/> either formally, or virtually, whereby all the Ordinances are adminiſtred, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrable among them. I ſhall iſſue this point into one Doctrinal Concluſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">6. <hi>Concl.</hi>
                  </note>The ſubordinate ordinary Power of acting Church-affairs, in the Order ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Jeſus Chriſt, for attainment of the ends of Church-Communion, is given by Chriſt to a viſible Congregation of confederate Believers, as the firſt and proper ſubject of it.</p>
               <p>In the handling of this point, I ſhall note ſomethings, 1. For Explication. 2. Confirmation of it. 3. Draw ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſectaries.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For explication of it, I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to clear five particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What I mean by <hi>Subordinate Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer.]</hi> Subordinate Power is that which wholly dependeth on Chriſts Ordinance and Inſtitution, who is the Supreme and only Monarch and Head of the Church; and therefore his revealed Will muſt be attended in all Church-Adminiſtations, as the only Rule, from which they may not ſwerve to the right hand, or to the left, for any humane policies, or pretences whatſoever, by adding ought thereto, or taking any thing therefrom. To this Chriſt limited his Apoſtles, who were the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:41503:52"/> higheſt Officers in the Church, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18, 19, 20. And, accordingly, <hi>Paul</hi> ſtrictly charged <hi>Timothy,</hi> and, in him, all the Churches and Church-Officers, <hi>to keep this Commandment, without ſpot, unrebukable, until the appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.13, 14, 15. They muſt aſſume to themſelves only that power, which he hath allotted them, and not exerciſe it any otherwiſe than he hath allowed them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Why I add <hi>ordinary,</hi> to ſubordinate.] It is added, to difference that Power, which reſideth in the Church for conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual uſe in ordinary diſpenſations, from that which was in the Apoſtles for a time, by the gift of Chriſt. Both Apoſtolical-Power, and Church-Power agree in this, that they are received immediately from Chriſt. For, as he ſaid to the Apoſtles, <hi>whoſe ſins ye remit, they are remitted,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.23. So he ſaid to the Church, both here, in <hi>Peter,</hi> and in <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Whatſoever ye ſhall bind, or looſe on earth,</hi> &amp;c. So that, neither did the Apoſtles re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their Power from the Church, nor doth the Church receive its power from the Apoſtles, but both immediatly from Chriſt: and therefore, as the Apoſtles had their Power, before viſible Chriſtian-Churches were conſtituted; ſo ſuch Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:41503:53"/> have and hold their Power, when Apoſtles ceaſe to be on earth. But herein theſe two Powers differ; 1. That Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Power was centred in one ſingle Perſon, and extended it ſelf to the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of all Churches. Each Apoſtle had the Power of the whole Church, and of all the Officers of the Church; when he was abſent from the Churches, he could adminiſter Seals and Cenſures, as if he had the preſence and concurrence of the Church: and, if he was preſent in any Church that wanted Officers, an Apoſtle had power to execute every Office, for the Church. And this their Power ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended it ſelf as much to all Churches, as to any one. <hi>Their Line went out into all the World, Pſal.</hi> 19.4. with <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.18. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. For as the Father ſent Chriſt the Mediator, with fulneſs of Soveragin Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer; ſo Chriſt ſent his Apoſtles with ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Miniſterial Power, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.21. But Church-Power is not in one man, but in a Society, and to be exerciſed vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly by ſeveral perſons in that ſociety, according to variety of callings. <hi>Are all Teachers?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.29. Hence, 2. That was extraordinary, and to laſt but for a time: but this is ordinary, and to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to the end. <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.1.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:41503:53"/>3. What <hi>the Church-Affairs are,</hi> and what <hi>the acting them</hi> imports.] The Church-affairs are the Ordinances of Chriſt, called here <hi>the Keys,</hi> in a large-ſenſe, the word of the Covenant, and the ſeals of the Covenant, and the Cenſures. Theſe the Church may be ſaid <hi>to act, by opening and ſhutting.</hi> 1. They open the doors of the Church ſubordinately, when they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit only ſuch, and all ſuch, to fellowſhip, whom Chriſt receiveth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.1, 3. 2. The doors of office in the Church they do open in the Church ſubordinately, when they elect and ordain ſuch unto Offices, as Chriſt hath prepared and called thereunto, according to the rule in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1-14. and then only to ſuch Offices as Chriſt hath ſet in his Church: which are only four, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.6, 7, 8. For Widows are included in Deacons. Theſe are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to two general heads, in <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. and ſo are their functions, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6, 7. and yeeld unto them all, and only that power which Chriſt hath annexed to their Office, and particularly unto Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Ruling Officers, that ſubjection and honour which the word calls for, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17, 18. 3. They ſhut the Doores of the Church, and binde men from Church—Ordinances,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:41503:54"/> and Priviledges; 1. By not admitting thoſe to Church-fellowſhip, againſt whom they have juſt exceptions, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.26. 2. By judging and cenſuring ſcandlaous mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, whether Brethren or Officers, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Chriſts Rules, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17, 18. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 3. By holding them under cenſure, without releaſe, till their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance be to ſatisfaction, according to Chriſt's Rules, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6, 7.</p>
               <p n="4">4. What <hi>the order is,</hi> wherein Chriſt will have theſe Church-affairs to be act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?] The order is this. Firſt, a company of Believers, being ſatisfied concerning the ſpiritual ſtate of one another, and their fitneſs for Church-fellowſhip, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon confederating together, to walk together in all the Ordinances of Chriſt, with mutual watchfulneſs and ſubmiſſion one to another in the Lord, become a Congregational-Church. They have now the eſſentials of a Church. 2. Being ſuch, they muſt look out from among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for ſuch Officers as Chriſt hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to his Church; theſe they muſt chuſe and ordain, profeſſing their voluntary ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to their Office-Rule, and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, in the Lord. Till this be done, they cannot compleatly act all Church-affairs, in due order. Till they have Teaching-Elders,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:41503:54"/> though there be gifted-Brethren among them that may Propheſie, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. yet they have none to <hi>give themſelves continually to Prayer</hi> (according to the neceſſities and occaſions of the Church) <hi>and to the Miniſtry of the Word, Act.</hi> 6.4. Such attendance being proper to Officers; <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.7. Nor, 3. <hi>to preach the word with authority,</hi> as an Officer muſt. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.15. Nor, 4. to adminiſter <hi>the Seals,</hi> which Chriſt hath annexed to the official preaching of the Word, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. Without Ruling-Elders, who ſhall call the Church together, as the Apoſtles did, on ſpeciall weighty occaſions, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.2? Who ſhall prepare matters for the Church, 1. By examining Officers or Members, before they be received of the Church, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.2. 2. By ſtating and clearing the queſtion and proofs, and trying, whether matters have been carried according to Rule, privatly, in the firſt and ſecond ſtep, before any offence be preſented to the Church, which was ſecret at firſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. 3. By directing thoſe that are to give ſatisfaction to the Church, in caſe of offence conceiv'd againſt them, how to carry themſelves, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to rule, to remove it, as the Apoſtles and Elders, being met at the Houſe of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:41503:55"/> 
                  <hi>James,</hi> did to <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 21.18. To theſe heads, other like caſes are to be referred. Who ſhall moderate debates in the Church Aſſembly, and order ſpeaking and ſilence in the Church, according to Rules of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and edification? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26, 40. Who ſhall hold forth light from the Rule, to guide the apprehenſions and judgment of the Brethren, in difficult caſes? accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.23, 24. Laſtly, who ſhall diſmiſs the Church Authoritatively, with a Bleſſing, in the name of the Lord? <hi>Numb.</hi> 6.23-26. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.7. And who ſhall take care of the humane affairs of the Church, if Deacons be not choſen and ordained? This Office-Power the Church indeed hath not <hi>formally</hi> in it ſelf; yet it hath it <hi>virtually,</hi> and <hi>originally.</hi> As the ſtock of a Tree hath not immediate po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to bring forth fruit, yet it hath po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to produce branches which do bring forth fruit; ſo the Church of Believers, though it hath not immediate power to act an Office, in the things proper there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, yet it hath power to make ſuch Officers as may perform the ſame in Chriſt's order.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Why this Power is ſaid to be given to a viſible Congregation of confederate Believers, as the firſt and proper ſubject
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:41503:55"/> of it?] This expreſſion ſerveth to ſhew three particulars. 1. That I ſpeak of a Congregational-Church, indefinitely, or the Church in its general nature, as it exiſts in particular Congregations, to each of which it communicates its whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and with it all its priviledges and power to them all, being ſpecies of it, firſtly and equally; ſo that each particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church hath all Church-Power, that is ſeated in the general nature of the Church, as compleatly conveyed to it, as any other: as this particular man, <hi>John,</hi> or <hi>Peter,</hi> or <hi>James</hi> hath all the nature of man equally communicated to them, and can put forth the operations of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, fully of themſelves, and without the help of any other. 2. That this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is given to the Church to be acted, in Admiſſions, Elections, and Cenſures, only by ſuch in whoſe name <hi>Peter</hi> made this confeſſion, <hi>viz. a Community of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples walking in the profeſſion of the Faith, with conſent;</hi> that is, to a Society of <hi>believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men:</hi> for Women, though Believers, are excepted by the Rule, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12-14. 2. <hi>Profeſſing Believers;</hi> therefore Children and diſtracted perſons are not capable of this power, being unfit <hi>to judge,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12. and ſo are they that are Deaf and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:41503:56"/> Dumb. 3. Such as <hi>walk in the profeſſion of the Faith, with conſent.</hi> Therefore ſuch as are under publick cenſure for ſcandals in Life or Doctrine, are diſabled, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, for the time, loſt their priviledge and power. Laſtly, if the Church it ſelf be generally corrupted or divided among themſelves, as it were into two equal parts, it cannot act this power, nor claim an intereſt in this promiſe, which is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to a Church aſſembly in Chriſts Name, with competent agreement among themſelves. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17, 18, 19, 20. 3. That this Power is given to ſuch a Church, not only objectively for their good, but ſubjectively and firſtly, ſo that the Church is the firſt recipient ſubject of it. For Officers are given to the Church, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8, 11. not as meer adjuncts are given to a ſubject, but as integral parts, for compleating the integrity and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the whole body of the Church: and, if they be ſo given to the Church, the Church is the recipient ſubject of them: and though the Church cannot by it ſelf exerciſe the Teaching and Ruling-Elders Office; yet they may by their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers; as the body, though it cannot ſee by it ſelf, yet it may by the eyes which are given to it for that end.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:41503:56"/>2. The Confirmation, or proof, that ſuch a Church is the firſt and proper ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this power; ſhall be double. 1. By Scripture. 2. By Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By Scripture, it may be proved from ſundry Texts. 1. This in hand clearly confirmeth it, if that good ancient rule of expounding Scripture be received, <hi>Dictorum intelligentia ex cauſis dictorum ſumenda eſt.</hi> For Chriſt's queſtion to the Diſciples, which was the cauſe of <hi>Peter's</hi> confeſſion here, was only concerning the Faith common to the Church. <hi>Whom ſay ye that I am?</hi> Hereupon <hi>Peter,</hi> in the name of the Diſciples, made this confeſſion of Faith.<note place="margin">Quia Chriſtus <hi>Petra, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus</hi> popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianus. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> in <hi>Matth.</hi> de verbis Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, <hi>Ser. 13.</hi>
                  </note> Chriſt teſtified his approbation of it, by calling him <hi>Peter,</hi> not ſo much in reſpect of his Office, as of his Faith thus publickly profeſſed, whence alſo viſible Believers are called <hi>lively ſtones,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4, 5. and Chriſt added to this praiſe of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> a twofold promiſe. 1. Of edifying and ſtabliſhing the Church, <hi>upon this Rock.</hi> 2. Of affording it ſufficient means for the attainment of thoſe ends, <hi>viz. the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. Where <hi>the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> or viſible Church of Chriſt on earth, is compared to a City, or Houſe, the Door or Gate whereof is Chriſt; the Keys are all inſtituted means,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:41503:57"/> whereby an entrance into Chriſt and his Kingdom, viſibly, is opened and ſhut, the ſubordinate power whereof is here given to the Church immediately.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Text is in <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17, 18. <hi>Tell the Church,</hi> &amp;, <hi>if he hear not the Church, let him be as an Heathen and a Publican. For what you ſhall bind on Earth, ſhall be bound in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. This cannot be meant of Elders aſſembling together, and acting apart from the Brethren. For no ſuch aſſembly is called the Church, in the New Teſtament, much leſs is this power given to them: for, in caſe of ſcandal given by them, they are under the power of the whole Church, as well as other Members, to be cenſured by them; though, when they keep the Rule, they are as El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Rulers in the Church. It muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be meant of a Congregational-Church. The third Text is in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. where <hi>Paul</hi> exhorted the Church at <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> to exerciſe this their power, which he calls <hi>the power of the Lord Jeſus, v.</hi> 4. whereby they were <hi>to deliver unto Satan</hi> that inceſtuous perſon; <hi>v.</hi> 5. and were to purge out the old leaven; <hi>v.</hi> 7. and were to judge thoſe that are within; <hi>v.</hi> 12. and <hi>to put away that wicked perſon from among them; v.</hi> 13. and this <hi>Paul</hi> calls a <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:41503:57"/> inflicted by many,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. Thus he eſtabliſheth their power to bind, and teacheth them how to uſe it; and, in like manner, he exhorteth them, upon the mans repentance, to turn the Key, and to open the Door of Chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to him, and to looſe him from the former cenſure, by forgiving him, in a legal or judicial ſenſe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7, 10. And that this Church at <hi>Corinth</hi> was a meer Congregational-Church, it may be evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from hence, that the whole Church was no larger, then was wont to meet together in one place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.23. for the ordinary worſhip of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe in ſuch a Congregational-Church are all the cauſes of this power. 1. Efficient; the Inſtitution and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Chriſt, who delegateth this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate power, to whom it pleaſeth him, by his own appointment. 2. The mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial cauſe; viſible Believers. 3. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal cauſe; Covenanting together to walk in all the Ordinances of Chriſt, and to ſubmit mutually one to another in the Lord; to be reclaimed, if they err from the rules; or to be cenſured by the power of the whole, if they be found obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:41503:58"/>2. Becauſe there is no former ſubject of this power, from whence a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional-Church might derive it, but it is communicated, by means of the Church, to all that partake of it, and it remaineth in the Church, when others are removed. They chooſe their own Elders: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had this power virtually in them before they had Elders, and ſo could not derive it from them. 2. All particular Churches are of equal power within themſelves, not one of them ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate to another. Therefore they derive it not from other particular Churches. 3. Synods, both leſſer and larger, are made up of the Elders and Meſſengers ſent from particular Churches, and have their being from them; nor do they ſend them to them, to borrow any Church-power, but only light from them; as the Church at <hi>Antioch</hi> did from the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem, Acts</hi> 15. Therefore they derive no Church-power from them. Again, when the Elders of particular Churches are dead, or cenſured, or reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the power of the whole for obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy in ſcandalous evils, the Church ſtill retaineth its power to chooſe others; as a Corporation hath its full power ſtill, though the Magiſtrates be dead, or caſt
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:41503:58"/> out. The ſame holds in Churches in Iſlands, by their own confeſſion, when they cannot have the help of Synods. Thus we prove Fire to be the firſt ſubject of heat, becauſe, if it be in other things, as in Water, or Wood; it is there by the means of Fire, and, when they are remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, yet ſtill it remains in Fire. The like reaſon holds in this, as you ſee, to prove ſuch a Church, as this of which we ſpeak, to be the firſt ſubject of Church-Power, or of the Keys.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe all the acts done immediatly by the Church, in opening and ſhutting, in binding and looſing, flow from this power of the Keys given them by Chriſt, and hold it forth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Their admitting Members is an act of this Power,</hi> and holds it forth: for, till the Brethren be ſatisfied, and approve ones fitneſs, he cannot be received into their fellowſhip; <hi>Act.</hi> 9.26. and 10.47.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Their chooſing Officers is an act of this Power,</hi> which the Apoſtles would not vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olate, in adding Deacons, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.3, 5. and Ruling-Elders to the Church, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. and the ſame holds much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Paſtors and Teachers. This po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer <hi>Cyprian</hi> acknowledged to be in the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:41503:59"/>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <p>Plebs obſequens praeceptis Dominicis &amp; Deum metuens, ipſa maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè habet poteſtatem vel eligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di dignos ſacerdotes vel indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandi.</p>
                     <p>Quod &amp; ipſum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus de Divinâ authoritate deſcendere. <hi>Cypr. l.</hi> 1. <hi>ep.</hi> 4.</p>
                  </note> People principally, to accept or refuſe Miniſters, as they judged them worthy or unworthy.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Their Ordination of Officers, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting ſome choſen out of their own Body thereunto (in the want of Officers) is an act of this Power</hi> of the Keys reſiding in them. For, though the Offices of Elders in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and the Authority of their Office, as they are Rulers, is from Chriſt imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately; yet the inveſting of this or that elect perſon with this Office &amp; Authority, in relation to this or that Church, by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of it to him in particular, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to another, this is by the Church.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">Ubi eſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, ibi eſſe neceſſe eſt jus eligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, et ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ndi Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtros. <hi>Melanct.</hi> de poteſt. Epiſcop. Arg. 2.</note>4. <hi>Their Expoſtulating with any Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, in caſe of ſuppoſed offence, is an act of this Power,</hi> whereunto <hi>Peter</hi> ſubmitted, though an Apoſtle, in the Church at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem. Act.</hi> 11.2, 3, 4.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Their publick Admoniſhing offenders, is an act of this Power,</hi> whether they be offending Brethren, or offending Officers, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Let him hear the Church,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Say to</hi> Archippus, <hi>Fulfil,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Their Excommunicating obſtinate and ſcandalous ſinners, whether a Brother,</hi> Mat. 18.18. 1 Cor. 5.4, 5. <hi>or an Officer,</hi> Gal. 5.12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:41503:59"/> 
                  <hi>is an act of this power in the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Their receiving again, or releaſing from cenſure, thoſe that have been under cenſure, upon their repentance, according to the Rule,</hi> 2 Cor. 2.7, 10. <hi>is an act of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ower.</hi> This alſo <hi>Cyprian</hi> acknowledged to be in the<note n="*" place="margin">Vix plebi perſuadeo, imò extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queo, ut tales pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitti. Et juſtior fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus eſt fraternita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis dolor, exeo, quod unus atque alius, obnitente plebe &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicente, meâ tamen facilitate ſuſcepti, priores extiterunt, quàm priùs fuerant, nec fidem poenitentiae ſervare potuerunt, quia nec cum verâ poenitentiâ venerant. <hi>Cypr. l.</hi> 1. <hi>ep.</hi> 3.</note> People, or fraternity, who, though they gladly received ſuch as returned with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, yet he could hardly perſwade them, yea, extort it from them, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſuch, in whom pride and obſtinacy appeared, and he juſtified them herein, blaming himſelf for too much facility.</p>
               <div n="1" type="corollary">
                  <head>1. <hi>Corollarie.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Then the Church is before its Officers, that is, it is a true Church, eſſentially, and hath all Church-Power, either for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally, or virtually, before it hath Officers, and when the Officers are removed from it, by Death or Cenſure. For, 1. as a man is a true man, who is a <hi>living creature endued with a reaſonable ſoul,</hi> becauſe the definition of a man agreeth to him, though he wanteth ſome bodily Members; ſo a Church is a true Church, which conſiſts of a <hi>Soc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> of viſible Believers confederated
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:41503:60"/> together in one Congregation, to walk toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in all the Ordinances of Chriſt, with mutual ſubmiſſion one to another, in the Lord;</hi> becauſe the definition of a Church agreeth to it, though it wants Officers. 2. Such a Church can call their Officers, and thereby make them Officers to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Therefore it muſt be before them, as the cauſe is before its effect. A Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration hath its being and power of a Corporation within it ſelf, before it hath Magiſtrates; becauſe it can chuſe Magiſtrates, and, when they are dead, or put out, can put others into their ſtead and place. So it is with the Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="corollary">
                  <head>2. <hi>Corollary.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Then though the Church hath its eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial being and power, without Officers; yet it is defective two wayes. 1. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Members, it hath not its compleat integrity of Members, without them. <hi>Bartimeus</hi> was a true man, without his eyes, but not perfect, with the integrity of his parts and members: ſo is the Church defective and mained without Officers. 2. As it is defective in its members, ſo alſo, in its operations, if it want Officers. For ſome Ordinances <hi>cannot be at all adminiſtred</hi> in the Churches, without Paſtors or Teachers as the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:41503:60"/> Seals, or Sacraments, which are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, by the Ordinance of Chriſt, to the Word of the Covenant, and the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of them is by him limited unto Preachers of the Word by Office, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. and ſome acts of Rule, as, in order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpeech in publick, in Church-debates, according to rules of order and edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the like, cannot be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Ruling-Elders. The ſame may be ſaid of Official watching, to prevent or remove private diſorders in converſation among the Members. 3. Some <hi>cannot be ſo done</hi> by others, as by Officers. 1. Not with that attendance to them, as the need and good of the Church requireth. <hi>He that hath an Office is bound to wait on it,</hi> Rom. 12.7. <hi>to give himſelf to the duties of it continually,</hi> Act. 6.4. <hi>to be in it,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.15. and therefore muſt be freed by the Church from other diſtracting cares, which would diſable him to it, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17, 18. 2. Not with Authority, which belongeth to Ruling Officers in the Church, as in preaching the Word with Authority, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. ſo in other acts, which be properly Official and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative. Hence ariſeth a difference between Officers and private Members, in their ſeve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> manner of acting in things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:41503:61"/> to both. A Church wanting Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, may appoint ſome of their Members to declare the mind of the Church, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the admiſſion of ſuch into the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Covenant, and Memberſhip with the Church, in whoſe fitneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the Church is ſatisfied; and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining Officers, choſen by the Church, by impoſition of hands and Prayer; and in gathering the ſuffrages of the fraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and in declaring the judgment of the Church in Cenſures: but theſe things they do, only at the appointment of the Church, <hi>pro hâc vel illâ vice.</hi> The ſame things are done by Teaching and Ruling-Elders in another manner, <hi>viz.</hi> by virtue of their Office, without particular leave of the Church: for, it belongs to them, as Officers, to attend unto their Work, not only to hold forth the Covenant, and to receive into Fellowſhip, in the name of the Church, thoſe whom the Church appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, but alſo to try the fitneſs of thoſe that offer themſelves unto Fellowſhip, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they propound them to the Church. The ſame holds in Officers to be called; and when the Church hath choſen them, and agreed to ordain them, the Elderſhip impoſe hands upon them, in the preſence of the Church, by virtue of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Office.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:41503:61"/> When offences are brought to the Church in the third ſtep, as the Elders do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the caſe, ſo it muſt firſt be notified to them, that they may try whether the Rule hath been attended in the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſteps, and that they may clear all dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, and then propound the caſe, when it is found to be fit for publick cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance, according to Rule. And being ſo, if they neglect to bring it to the Church, or aſſume any undue power to themſelves, they that are offended may complain to the Church; and, as need may require, they are to hold forth light from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to guide the Church in judging: and, in the cloſe, to propound the ſentence (wherein the Church conſenteth, and they concur with them) authoritatively.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="corollary">
                  <head>3. <hi>Corollary.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Then the proper acts of Church-power, and of ordinary Office-power, are limited, by the Ordinance of Chriſt, to be put forth by the Church, and Officers reſpectively, within that Body, or particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, to which they have a particular memberly or official Relation. The mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of one Church cannot act in admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Members, chooſing the Officers, nor cenſuring Offenders of another Churc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Nor may the Officers of one
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:41503:62"/> Church, adminiſter the Seals, or ordain Officers, or perform other proper Acts of official Authority, out of their own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, in another Church. The Church may, by communion of Churches, upon orderly, recommendation, receive the members of other Churches unto fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of ſuch Ordinances, as are for the comfort and ſtrengthning of the Saints, as the Seals are, and the Officers may admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter them to ſuch, being accepted by the body: for we have a warrant for ſo much, from the Rule, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.1. 3 <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. but not to act in judgement. For, the Church hath this priviledge proper to be judged by, and to judg, only thoſe that are within, <q>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12. whereas I alledged this Text againſt Mr. <hi>Paget,</hi> to prove, that Church-Ordinances belong only to the Members of ſome particular Church, Mr. <hi>Rutterf.</hi> meeting with that expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſaith, Mr. <hi>D.</hi> will have Paſtors ſo far ſtrangers to all Congregations, ſave their own, that (he ſaith) other Churches are without, and have nothing to do to judge them, and alledgeth for this, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12. But by thoſe that are without, <hi>Paul</hi> meaneth, not thoſe that were not of the Congregation, but he meaneth In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels and Heathen, as in other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:41503:62"/> For <hi>Paul</hi> judged and excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20. who were without the Church at <hi>Corinth.</hi>]</q> Had Mr. <hi>Rutt.</hi> been pleaſed to caſt his eye upon my own defence of that paſſage,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>In my</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, pag. 312, 313.</note> printed ſundry years before he put pen to paper in theſe diſputes about Church affairs, he might have found that written by me, touching the ſenſe, and my application of that Text, which might have prevented his exagitating that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Nor doth he with any congruity argue from <hi>Pauls</hi> Excommunicating <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> who, he ſaith, <hi>were without the Church at Corinth,</hi> to prove that Paſtors have any thing to do, to judge judicially, or excommunicate the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of other Congregations. For <hi>Paul</hi> was an Apoſtle, an extraordinary Officer, had an illimited commiſſion, and a fulneſs of delegated power both in every Church, and to adminiſter Church-Ordinances, without the fellowſhip of a particular Church, when it could not be had; and to execute all Offices in any Church, where Officers were wanting: But Paſtors are ordinary Officers, have a limited com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, to do only the acts of the Paſtoral Office, and thoſe only to that particular Church by which they are called unto
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:41503:63"/> Office; <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2. Therefore, though <hi>Paul</hi> might excommunicate one that was not of that particular Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> yet the Paſtor to the Church at <hi>Corinth</hi> might not. Yet <hi>Paul</hi> could not excommunicate one that was no member of any Church, but without, as Infidels and Heathen are: For that implies a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction. To conclude. The Apoſtle doth ſo appropriate Church-judgment, to thoſe that are within that particular Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Ye judge them that are within;</hi> that he exempts from it in a due proportion, all that are not members of that Congregation; though there are degrees of being without, ſome being totally without all Church-communion, as Infidels and Heathen: others, though in Church-communion elſe-where, yet not in communion of memberſhip of that Church, to whom he wrote to <hi>put away from them;</hi> not one that was a member of another Church, but him that was a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of that Church. And, in this ſenſe, Mr. <hi>Rutt.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> were <hi>without the Church at Corinth,</hi> though members of ſome other Church: for which cauſe, the Church at <hi>Corinth</hi> could not excommunicate them, yet <hi>Paul</hi> might, and did, by his Apoſtolical Power Thus,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:41503:63"/> by his own confeſſion, ſome are without a particular Church, who yet are not <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> or <hi>Infidels.</hi> To conclude, one may be ſaid to be without this or that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church, two ways. 1. Simply and abſolutely; ſo, <hi>Infidels</hi> and <hi>Heathen</hi> that are of no Church. 2. Comparatively, ſo the Members of other Churches, compared with thoſe that are of this Body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="corollary">
                  <head>4. <hi>Corollary.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Then Churches gathered, and Officers ordained, in theſe days, without Apoſtles, are true Churches, and true Church-Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, according to Chriſt; and Churches thus Organized, according to the Rules of the Word, are true, and intire Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and the firſt ſubject of all Church-power, as well as thoſe Primitive Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches planted by the Apoſtles. For the concurrence of the Apoſtles is not put into this Charter, whereof we ſpeak, as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Clauſe; which might not have been omitted, if Chriſt had intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that it ſhould be always neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. He doth not ſay, upon this Rock my Apoſtles ſhall build my Church, and to my Church built by them I will give the Keys of the Kingdom; but, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Rock I will build my Church (<hi>viz.</hi> by ſuch Inſtruments as Chriſt will raiſe,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:41503:64"/> and uſe, and bleſs in that work, in every Age;) and to this Church, thus built, he gives the Keys of the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. <hi>Object.</hi> But Chriſt gave the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of gathering Churches to his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, in <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18, 19. And, <hi>when he aſcended up on high, he gave ſome A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers, for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry,</hi> and for the edifying of the Body of Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8, 11, 12. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thoſe and the like Texts of Scripture do indeed ſhew, that God uſed Apoſtles prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally in this work, but not only: For as to Teach and Baptize is common to other Teaching-Officers, as well as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; ſo the gathering of Churches, by making men Diſciples of Chriſt, was done by others, beſides Apoſtles, even in the Apoſtles days, <hi>Act.</hi> 11.20, 21. The diſperſed Diſciples planted the Church at <hi>Antioch,</hi> the Members whereof were firſt called Chriſtians, a Church whoſe plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Barnabas</hi> approved, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. 2. They ſhew, that God would uſe Apoſtles here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, for a time, but not alwayes; which I prove, 1. From the proper work com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, to them, which was to make the firſt Models and Patterns of planting and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:41503:64"/> gathering Churches, which ordinary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentts are bound to attend in the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering and conſtituting of Churches, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6, 10. and, in that ſenſe, their work continues to the end of the World, though their manner of working. <hi>viz.</hi> from an immediate Call, Inſpiration, and Infallible aſſiſtance, proper to Apoſtles, in making thoſe Patterns, was extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ended with their Office, in the firſt Age, ſince when, there never have been Apoſtles in the World. For, though <hi>Matthias</hi> ſucceeded in the place of <hi>Judas,</hi> by Gods Election, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.26. yet after <hi>James</hi> was beheaded, no Apoſtle was choſen to ſucceed him, though the Apoſtles lived long after. 2. The Apoſtle <hi>John,</hi> who lived longeſt of the Apoſtles, deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, by Revelation from Chriſt, all the Officers that ſhould be, by Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, in Chriſtian Churches, after that Age, under four ſorts of living Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which note the four ſorts of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Officers to continue in the Church after that Age, <hi>viz.</hi> Paſtors, Teachers, Ruling-Elders, and Deacons, <hi>Revel.</hi> 4.1, 6, 7.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:41503:65"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 19.</hi>
                     </bibl> And whatſoever thou ſhalt bind on Earth, ſhall be bound in Heaven: Whatſoever thou ſhalt looſe on Earth, ſhall be looſed in Heaven.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THeſe words hold forth the Ratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt's grant of the Keys unto a Congregational-Church, with the chiefty of power, under Chriſt, to manage the ſame within themſelves, for the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of the ends of Church-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; And that this is ſpoken to <hi>Peter,</hi> in the name of ſuch a Church, and, that Chriſt intended to eſtabliſh, by this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, the compleat exerciſe of this power in ſuch a Church, being compleated with all it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Officers, is clear from <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.18. where the ſame promiſe is given, by name to ſuch a Church. The words therefore, in ſumme, hold forth a grant from Chriſt to his Church of an indiſpenſable power of Church-cenſures, within themſelves: which may be thus evinced. The cenſure that is eſtabliſhed in Heaven cannot be diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with, nor reverſed by any power on Earth: But the cenſure, that is admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by a Congregational-Church, is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in Heaven: Therefore it cannot be diſpenſed withall, nor reverſed by any
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:41503:65"/> power on Earth. The Propoſition, a man would think might paſs without oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but I find this Objection made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. <hi>Obj.</hi> The ſentence of an inferiour Judge or Court proceeding rightly, is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in Heaven; yet we may appeal from it; Why will not the ſame hold in Church-cenſures alſo? <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Becauſe the promiſe of binding in Heaven, is not given by Chriſt to the cenſures of Civil Courts: For it is not a Civil, but a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual binding that is here meant. 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is not <hi>par ratio</hi> between them. The reaſon why appeals may be made from the ſentence of inferiour Civil Courts and Judges, is, becauſe there is a Supreme Court <hi>in being,</hi> to which the appeal may be brought, and there proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, and thereby determined (as the inferiour Courts in <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſtood under the higheſt Synedrion;) but there is no ſuch Supreme Court ordained by Chriſt over particular Churches. The Aſſumption, That the cenſure that is adminiſtred by a Congregational-Church is eſtabliſhed in Heaven, is expreſly in the Text, as it hath been expounded. True, ſay ſome, what a particular Church binds on Earth, <hi>clave non errante,</hi> is bound in Heaven, but the Church may err in Judgement, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:41503:66"/> appeal may be made, and then their binding power is gone. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. If poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of erring in Judgment be a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable ground of appealing from parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches; then the appeal muſt be made to ſuch a Tribunal and Judge, as cannot err, which is to be found only in Heaven. 2. On this ground, the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Church repreſented in a general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil (much more, inferiour <hi>Synods</hi> and <hi>Claſſes</hi>) ſhould not have power to bind, without appeals. For a general Council may err, and hath erred; not ſeldom, but often; not in ſmall matters only, but in thoſe of the greateſt moment; yea they may be as much inclined to err, as parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches: For the greateſt part of viſible Churches in the World are for the moſt part corrupt. If it be ſaid, There are more eyes, <hi>&amp; plus vident oculi quam oculus?</hi> I anſwer; True, <hi>caeteris paribus, viz.</hi> if they are equally near the mark; but their ſight is hindred more than par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches are in their proper con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments, as they are further from the mark, in ſuch caſes, than particular Churches. And if particular Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches have not full power of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, becauſe they may err, be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, be partial, be divided; upon the ſame
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:41503:66"/> ground, neither Claſſical, National, not Oecumenical Aſſemblies have any ſuch power; for they may err, be corrupt, be partial, be divided alſo. 3. Chriſt, who well knew what is in man, and what is beſt for the good of his people, hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto his particular Churches, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their poſſibility of erring, an indiſpenſable power of judgment, in their own matters, within themſelves. The Doctrinal Concluſion to be inſiſted upon, is this:</p>
               <p>A Congregational Church of Chriſt,<note place="margin">7. <hi>Conclu.</hi>
                  </note> being compleated with Officers, hath, by the gift of Chriſt, within it ſelf, compleat ſubordinate Church-power in all Church-affairs proper to it ſelf. When I ſay, 1. It hath compleat, or ſufficient Church-power] Thereby I mean, 1. That it needeth not the influence of the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Juriſdiction of any other Church or Churches, or Claſſes, or Synods, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply unto it any power that it wanteth, in its own matters; and 2. That it ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not in ſubjection under any other Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior Eccleſiaſtical Judicatory, ſo as that thereby the judicial Acts of a particular Church may be hindered, or made void. In a word, <hi>Poteſtas uniuſcujuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris Eccleſiae, in re propria, ſumma eſt. The
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:41503:67"/> power of ſuch a Church is Chief,</hi> in things proper to it ſelf. 2. I add, that <hi>this chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of power,</hi> in a particular Church, <hi>is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate</hi>] To ſhew, that the abſolute Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy of power is in Chriſt; that which the Church hath, is only delegated from Chriſt. When a particular Church is compleated with all its Officers, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of it, in reſpect of Chriſt the Head, is perfectly Monarchical; in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Elders, acting their Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or Office-power, it is Ariſtocratical; and in reſpect of the Fraternity, acting its Chuch-power in Judgment, it is De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocratical; and, in the concurrence of all the Members, both Officers and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, acting according to their ſeveral intereſts, it is <hi>Ariſtocratico-Democratical;</hi> above which, Chriſt hath not ſet any higher Eccleſiaſtical Judicatory on Earth, ſubjecting particular Churches thereunto, <hi>in re propriâ.</hi> A clear proof of ſuch pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as that which hath been deſcribed, you may ſee in the Church at <hi>Corinth</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicating that inceſtuous perſon, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1-5. Say not, as ſome do, That was not an act of Judicial power in that Church, but of ſubjection to the Apoſtle who decreed it, and judged him before, and committed no more to the Church,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:41503:67"/> but the publiſhing of the ſentence; for,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, 1 Cor. 5.3.</note> though <hi>Paul,</hi> as an Apoſtle, judged that he ſhould be excommunicated, yet he ſo judged only dogmatically, by teaching the Church what they ought to do in that caſe, not judicially, by his own ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, delivering him to Sathan; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ordingly <hi>the Church caſt him out,</hi> by their own ſufficiency of Church-power, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in themſelves, though in a way of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the command of Chriſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by <hi>Paul.</hi> For, 1. They <hi>delivered him to Satan, in the Name, and with the Power of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> v. 4. and that is the higheſt Power. 2. The end and uſe of it was, <hi>for the deſtruction of the fleſh, that his Spirit might be ſaved in the day of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> v. 5. which argueth, that it proceedeth from a power of binding in Heaven, as well as on Earth. 3. When God bleſſed this ſentence, by making it effectual to work Repentance in him, <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth the whole Church to releaſe and forgive him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6-10. and doth not claim the Power over them of a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Judge, to abſolve him by his own ſentence, without them: Nor did he write to the Elders of ſundry Churches, but only to that particular Church, both Elders and Brethren, and thereby ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:41503:68"/> the Power of Eccleſiaſtical Judgment to be ſo fully in them, that, As their not putting it into act retarded the ſentence before, and their putting of it into act was a Judicial Act in them all, <hi>ye judge them that are within,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.12. So, their forgiving him would be a Legal and Judicial acquitting him from tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſentence, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. This Church is our pattern, and its practice in this is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidential to all particular Churches of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> From the guilt which lyeth upon every ſuch Church, when any ſcandal given by their Members remaineth uncenſured and unremoved. Therefore <hi>Paul</hi> applyed this Reproof to the whole Church, Brethren as well as Officers, for their ſlowneſs to excommunicate that man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2. And in like manner, Chriſt reproveth the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, and Church, both of <hi>Pergamus,</hi> Rev. 2.14, 15. and of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> ver. 20. If theſe Churches had not ſufficient power within themſelves to purge out ſuch Leaven, why are they blamed for tolerating the ſame? And why are not other Churches, or the Claſſes, blamed for neglect of exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing their power of Eccleſiaſtical Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture over them, if they ſtood under any ſuch? And what the Spirit ſpeaketh to
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:41503:68"/> them, he ſaith to other Churches alſo, to beware of the like Remiſneſs. Which Admonition all particular Churches are bound to attend; leſt elſe the gates of Hell prevail againſt them, through their neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of exerciſing that power which Chriſt hath given them, ſeverally, and reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, to preſerve their Members and whole fellowſhip in Spiritual purity and ſafety, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> From the Analogy and agreement that is between the Spiritual power of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational Church of Chriſt, and the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil power of the moſt free and perfect Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which <hi>Thucidides</hi> ſaith have three priviledges, <hi>viz.</hi> to uſe, 1. Their own Laws. 2. Magiſtrates. 3. Judgments, (whence he cals every ſuch City, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) other Cities were not account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed intire and perfect Cities of themſelves, but leſs worthy Members of thoſe great and perfect Cities,<note place="margin">Grot. de jure bel &amp; pac. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>4, 5, 7.</hi>
                  </note> under whoſe Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction they were. The <hi>ſumma poteſtas of thoſe great and perfect Cities, is that, cujus actus alterius juri non ſubſunt, ita ut alteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us voluntatis humanae arbitrio irriti poſſunt reddi.</hi> Now every particular Church of Chriſt, being compleated with its Officers, is a moſt perfect and free City, <hi>the City of God,</hi> Pſal. 48.1. <hi>The City of the great King,</hi>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:41503:69"/> ver. 2. the viſible Kingdom of <hi>the bleſſed and only Potentate, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.15. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt neceſſarily have ſufficient and compleat power within it ſelf to manage the Keys, without dependence on Claſſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in its own concernments. Yet herein is a difference between ſuch perfect Cities and the Churches of Chriſt, That ſuch Cities may part with their Liberty, in ſome caſes,<note place="margin">Liv. Dec. <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> Idem. Ibid. l. <hi>7.</hi> Populum Campa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lubra De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ûm, divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> omnia in veſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>P.C.</hi> ditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note> as being overmatched by a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Enemy. In this caſe, the <hi>Collatives</hi> yielded up themſelves, and their City and Liberties to <hi>Tarquinius Priſcus</hi> King of the <hi>Romans;</hi> or when they are in extream danger by an Enemy, whom they would not have to rule over them, and cannot defend themſelves by any other means, which was the caſe of <hi>Campani</hi> diſtreſſed by the <hi>Samnites,</hi> which forced them to yield up themſelves, and all they had, with all their Liberties, unto the <hi>Romans;</hi> which when they had done, they were ſaid to be <hi>facti alienae poteſtatis.</hi> Yet it was preſuppoſed that they had power in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves thus to do, as appears by that queſtion, <hi>Eſtne populus Collatinus in ſuâ poteſtate?</hi> But Churches have not power to alienate from themſelves their Church-Liberties, which Chriſt hath purchaſed
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:41503:69"/> for them with his Blood, and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to <hi>ſtand faſt</hi> in them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. and, to whom they muſt give an account, how they have kept and managed the ſame, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.2.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> From the Conceſſion of thoſe that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this Truth.<note place="margin">The pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of <hi>Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and <hi>Syn.</hi> p. 33. <hi>ad Calcem.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <q>Mr. <hi>Pag.</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth that if a particular Church of God ſhould ſojourn among the <hi>Indians,</hi> or among <hi>Hereticks,</hi> where it could not obtain fellowſhip with other Churches out of it ſelf: Or, if by violence, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unavoidable inconveniences, any Church ſhould be hindred from enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this benefit of combination with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches in Claſſical Government, yet notwithſtanding this want, this Church ſhould ſubſiſt ſtill, and be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a true Church.] Others ſay the ſame of a Church in an Iſland, and add,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> Herle Indep. p. <hi>2</hi>
                     </note> that, in ſuch caſes a ſingle Congregation muſt not be denyed intireneſs of Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</q> 
                  <q>Mr. <hi>Rutterf.</hi> adds, that when Churches cannot injoy the ſociety of neighbouring Churches with that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and conveniency as their occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may require, among them Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo Excommunication, may be performed by the Congregation.]</q> From this Conceſſion it will follow, that,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:41503:70"/>1. A Congregational Church of Chriſt, <hi>quà talis,</hi> hath a lawful right in an intire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Church-Government, within it ſelf, by the gift of Chriſt, yea, that the Church-power, Natively and Naturally, lyes in the Congregation, for ſuch caſes are ordinary; and the firſt Synod, which is looked at as preſidential to all Synods, was a concurrence of two Churches, which were two hundred miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The other Churches, or Claſſes, or Synods, have no right to take away this power from it. <hi>For none may put aſunder what God hath joyned,</hi> as well in this caſe, as in that noted in <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.7. God hath joyned intireneſs of Juriſdiction, <hi>in re pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priâ,</hi> to a particular Church, who then ſhall ſunder it from ſuch a Church, to place it in Claſſes, as Superior Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, where God never put it?</p>
               <p n="3">3. If the firſt Church in a Continent had this compleat power within it ſelf, before other Churches were gathered, and the riſing up of other Churches there long after, ſhould deprive them of it, by ſetting up a Claſſis, as a Superior Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, over them; then the neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Churches ſhould not be a benefit, but a diſadvantage to them, and would
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:41503:70"/> give them cauſe to complain unto God, Thou haſt multiplyed the Nation,<note place="margin">Pow. <hi>of</hi> Claſſ. &amp; Syn. p. <hi>33.</hi> Idem. p <hi>34.</hi>
                  </note> but not increaſed our joy. <q>But they hold, that every Church is bound to ſeek this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency and union with other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as God ſhall give opportunity and means, and cannot, without ſin, neglect the ſame. And, leſt we ſhould think it but a matter Arbitrary, at beſt; they tell us, it is of the ſame neceſſity, for a Church to combine unto Claſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and Synods, for their Spiritual Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if they have opportunity, as to joyn a mans ſelf, as a Member, to a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church, if he hath means and opportunity to do it; and conclude, all that neglect to do it, ſin againſt the Communion of Saints, and walk not as becometh the Body of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.15. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.16.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The Proofs alleadged do ſhew, that the Communion of Saints ought to be preſerved and exerciſed in Church-Communion by Believers, joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a particular Congregation, and walking in a Memberlike affection and fellowſhip with their Brethren, unto mutual edification; but they ſpeak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for the ſubjection of particular Churches to Claſſes and Synods, in <hi>re
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:41503:71"/> propriâ,</hi> but rather intimate the contrary: For the Apoſtle, by comparing a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational-Church compleated with its Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, unto the Body of a man intire in all its Members, ſheweth, that as the Body of a man, being intire and ſound, hath compleat power within it ſelf, for all bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily actions; ſo a particular Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing organized, and governed by Chriſt, <hi>the Head, from whom the whole Body fitly joyned and compacted together, by Joynts of ſupply, according to the effectual working in the meaſure of every part, maketh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the body, unto the edifying of it ſelf in love,</hi> Epheſ. 4.15, 16. without the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of any Juriſdiction out of it ſelf, to ſupply a Superior Church-power, which was wanting in this Body of Chiriſt, a Congregational-Church; and as the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Natural, being ſound and of a good conſtitution, hath ſufficient ability in it ſelf, to purge out of it ſelf Malignant Humors; ſo ſuch a Church hath ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent power in it ſelf, to caſt out vicious and hurtful Members, without the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of Claſſical Juriſdiction over them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is a ſin againſt the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment in ſuch, as having means and opportunity, neglect to joyn, as Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:41503:71"/> in a particular Congregation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is God's Ordinance, and revealed Will, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. But Claſſical Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction over particular Churches, and their ſubjection thereunto, is no Ordinance of Chriſt, and therefore it is ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neceſſary, that it is not lawful; but againſt the ſecond Commandment, which forbiddeth mens inventions in God's wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that it may eſtabliſh only God's Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances therein. Others argue thus: <q>As, though a Town or Family, being alone, may govern, as a compleat Body; yet, when it ſtands in a Common-wealth, it may not be ſo independent, but muſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to Combinations: So, though when a particular Congregation is alone, it may govern as compleat, yet not ſo, when it is among other Churches.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. There is not a like reaſon of Churches, and of Towns or Families in this reſpect. For civil Societies are more left to Rules of Humane prudence, by the great Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of the World, than Churches are. Therefore civil Societies may be of ſeveral conſtitutions, have dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Laws and Priviledges, and admit various forms of Government; provided that they be not againſt Moral Rules and the good of the People. But in this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:41503:72"/> Kingdom of Chriſt, men may not alter the kind or Form of Church, which Chriſt hath Inſtituted, but muſt preſerve inviolate the Laws, Adminiſtrations, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and Church-Government or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by him, without Addition, Dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution, or alteration. Hence a particular Church may not alienate from it ſelf, in whole, or part, any Right, Power or Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge given it by Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If ſuch a Town or Family hath compleat power and Officers within it ſelf, it is not bound to ſubmit to ſuch Combinations in a Common-wealth, except it be under a Superiour Power that can command the ſame. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> having a compleat Family, was not bound to combine with the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he dwelt amongſt, nor did he; though he joyned in a League of amity, and for mutual help, with <hi>Aner, Eſchol,</hi> and <hi>Mamre,</hi> yet not to ſubmit to their Government: So neither is a particular Organical Church bound to ſubmit to ſuch Claſſical Combinations, till it can be proved by Scripture, that a Superior Power of other Churches can command the ſame.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Though ſeveral Families, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving compleat Government within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:41503:72"/> muſt combine in a Common-wealth, yet not to yield up their Family-Government over their Wives, Children, and Servants, reſpectively, to rule them in common with other Maſters of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. Much leſs may ſeveral Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional-Churches give up the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of themſelves to Paſtors of ſundry Churches, combined in a Claſſis, to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern them in their proper Affairs, ſuch as Admiſſion of Members, Election and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of Officers, Adminiſtration of Seals and Cenſures.</p>
               <div n="1" type="corollary">
                  <head>1. <hi>Corollary.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Then the cenſure of Excommunication is not a light matter, but to be looked at, as very weighty and formidable. You ſee,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That it is the Soveraign Remedy preſcribde by Chriſt againſt the many Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, whereunto the Body is ſubject; the great preſervative of the Churches peace, and ſafety againſt the gates of Hell.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That it is ſuch a Power given by Chriſt to his Church, as proveth Church-Societies to be the viſible Suburbs of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, yea, the Kingdom of Heaven be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun on Earth, ſeeing ſuch an Heavenly Power is committed to them. This is a greater work than <hi>Elijah</hi> did, when he
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:41503:73"/> ſhut up Heaven, that it rained not, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.17. For that was but an outward and temporal Judgment, for three years and ſix moneths: But this is Spiritual, and for ever, upon impenitent perſons. It is greater than Earthly Kings and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates can do; they can bind a Malefactor hand and foot, and deliver him to the Jaylor, and ſentence him to baniſhment out of their Dominions: but this Cenſure binds the Soul and Conſcience, delivers them to Satan, and excludes obſtinate impenitent ſinners from the Kingdom of God; that when this Cenſure is applyed by the Church according to Scripture-Rules, Jeſus Chriſt <hi>is with them,</hi> to rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his Cenſure according to this Promiſe, <hi>What you ſhall bind on Earth, ſhall be bound in Heaven;</hi> and to bleſs it to the attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of its end, <hi>the deſtruction of the fleſh, that the Spirit may be ſaved.</hi> This is a ſingular Priviledge of Church-Members. If they that are out of Church-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, bleſs themſelves in their Liberty, becauſe they cannot be touched with Church-cenſures, they ſhew their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream folly therein; for they are left to the Sword of the Magiſtrate, or to the immediate judgment of God, as forlorn Creatures, excluded from Spiritual helps
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:41503:73"/> ſuitable to their needs. They are <hi>as Sheep whom no man taketh up,</hi> or careth for, in a Spiritual way, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.13, 14. It is therefore a ſpecial priviledge of Church-Members, and much for the furtherance of their eternal Salvation, if they improve it aright, to the mortifying of thoſe corruptions in them which could not be purged out and healed by eaſier means. And this is the proper end of it, that, ſeeing themſelves, as <hi>Adam,</hi> driven from the Tree of Life, by the flaming Sword of a Cherubim; or, as <hi>Cain,</hi> caſt out from Gods face; or, as the <hi>Leper,</hi> ſhut out from the fellowſhip of God's people; or, as that Inceſtuous <hi>Corinthian,</hi> delivered up to Satan, they may be aſhamed, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and effectually brought to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and to hold it forth according to God's Rules. If it work not this effect, the fault is their own: Yet it will not be without effect. For as the Goſpel is the ſavour of Death unto Death, when it is not the ſavour of Life unto Life; ſo this Goſpel-Ordinance ſhall not be in vain, but ſhall work, one way, or t'other, either the deſtruction of the impenitent, or the ſalvation of thoſe that repent. That therefore it may be effectual for their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal good, it is their duty, when the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:41503:74"/> ſentence proceeds, either according to the eighteenth of <hi>Matthew,</hi> upon their not hearing the Church, in leſs hainous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences; or, according to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15. upon the hainous nature of ſcandals given by them againſt common light, <hi>to humble themſelves under the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hand of God, that he may exalt them in due time,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.6. and to cry mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to him, to add efficacy to his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, by his Spirit, that their ſpirits may be duly and truly humbled, their corruptions powerfully mortified, and their ſouls eternally ſaved. Be ſure, that you take not part with your ſin againſt the Ordinance, but take part with the Ordinance againſt your ſin; and account it your honour, to honour God, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt his Rules; and let others learn here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to fear, not joyning with the Church, but perſiſting obſtinately in ſin.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="corollary">
                  <head>2. <hi>Corollary.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Then a Congregational Church (ſuch as hath been deſcribed) is the higheſt Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Tribunal, under Chriſt, in its own matters. This was revealed to <hi>John,</hi> as that frame of Church-Government which ſhould continue, from the Apoſtles time, unto the end of the World; when he ſaw a Throne ſet in Heaven, the Trinity
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:41503:74"/> ſitting upon it, and the four living Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures between it, and the four and twenty Elders who ſate round about the Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.1,-9. Thither appeals muſt be made according to Chriſt his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, by an offended Brother, after the firſt and ſecond ſtep; or by any Member that finds himſelf over-rigorouſly deal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with by his Brethren in theſe ſteps; <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17, 18. that there the Cauſe may be ſcanned, and Sentence proceed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Chriſt. If the Church want ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient light, or conſent, for the ſentence, they are to ſeek help from others by their Light and Counſel, but ſtill preſerving the power of Cenſure intirely in the Church, where Chriſt hath placed it. The wiſdom of Chriſt, the good of the Church, and of every Member, and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing require, that there be ſome chief Tribunal in the exerci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of Church-Government, unto which Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals muſt be laſt made, Juridically, and from which no Appeal may be granted and expected. 2. That this chief Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal muſt have no Eccleſiaſtical Power above it; and 3. That it may not be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially cenſured by any Power of the ſame kind. All the queſtion is, which is the chief Tribunal? That, ſay ſome, muſt be
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:41503:75"/> the Claſſes, under which ſuch Churches ſtand, and the Synods under which the Claſſes are ſubordinate; and they give this Reaſon: Becauſe the end, for which the Keys are given to the Church, is, that all offences may be removed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15, 16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which, they ſay, cannot be done, if you put the chief Power of Judgment into a Congregational Church. For, what if an Elder? what if the whole Ederſhip? yea, what if the whole Church offend? The Church cannot cenſure their Elders; for that were to rule their Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and to judge their Judges; nor will they cenſure themſelves. But a Claſſis or Synod of many Elders may, and will, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form all, by judicially cenſuring all.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. This Argument is built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a miſtake or error in the foundation of it. For the Rule preſcribed in <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t for removal of all offences, but of ſuch private and leſs hainous offences as grow publick and notorious, only by the obſtinacy of the Delinquent. For, if of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences be publick and heinous in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the Apoſtle doth not direct Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to proceed by thoſe ſteps, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Nor doth it make the People Rulers of their Rulers, or Judges of their Judges,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:41503:75"/> when we ſay, that the Church hath a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over them, in caſe of Delinquency. For Excommunication is not an act of the higheſt Rule, or Authority, but of the higheſt Judgment; and therefore the Power of it may well be in the whole Church, as their Priviledge, without any intrenchment upon the Rule and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Elders, wherein, as Officers, they are above the Brethren, whilſt they act accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Rule: But, if they become Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, then as Members, they are under the Power of the whole. The Church muſt ſubmit to them, as Rulers, whil'ſt they rightly exerciſe the Authority of their Office, in Preaching, Adminiſtring the Seals, holding forth light from Scripture to guide them in cenſure, ordering Speech and Silence according to Rules of Order and Edification, and in other Official Acts: But they muſt ſubmit to the Church, queſtioning, or proceeding to cenſure them with good advice of Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour-Churches and Elders; (who as they concurred in giving them the right hand of fellowſhip in their Ordination, ſo they ſhould concur in approving this Cenſure, as juſtly inflicted by the Church, from parity of reaſon.) The Mayor in a free City, or Corporation, is, in the right Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:41503:76"/> of his Office, above the Court, none but he can perform the Acts pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to his place; yet, if he corrupt the People, pervert Juſtice, or be, any way, groſly and ſcandalouſly delinquent, the Court can cenſure and deſpoſe him. For the whole hath Power over any Member, to preſerve its purity, and peace, and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty againſt any in the Body, that would corrupt, diſturb or deſtroy the ſame. And the Covenant binds every Member, to be ſubject to the Power of the whole, either to be reformed, or removed from commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of it thereby.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Their Plaiſter is not ſuitable to heal the Sores of the Church, but it is either too broad, when offences of Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren may be healed by Church-cenſure, within themſelves, or, it is too narrow.</p>
                  <p>For, 1. Thoſe Aſſemblies are too ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and cannot ſit together long enough to remove the many offences that fall out frequently in Churches.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Non can they Excommunicate a Church, nor any Officer or Member of a particular Chuch by warrant from Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Claſſes, and Synods, and general Councils may be under juſt offences, as well as Churches; and who ſhall cenſure them?</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="139" facs="tcp:41503:76"/>4. This Plaiſter hinders the healing of the Sores of Churches. For,<note place="margin">Appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio eſt jus, per quod prima ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſper ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguitur, donec de cauſae cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitione ad ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutâ, fuerit pronunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atum.</note> if a Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, diſliking the Churches proceeding, appeals from the ſentence of the Church to the Claſſis, and, for the ſame reaſon, from the ſentence of the Claſſis to a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Synod, then, to a National Synod, then to an Oecumenical Council, which may not aſſemble in an Age; while the Appeal depends, he ſhall ſtand as uncenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. For this is the Law of Appeals. Now, how can that heal which is croſs to the preſcription of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the only wiſe Phyſician? He ſaith, <hi>Tell the Church; and if he neglect to hear the Church, let him be unto thee as an Heathen &amp; Publican.</hi> But he who appeals from the Church, doth not hear the Church. Therefore he that ſo doth, deſerves to be cut off, by the ſentence of Chriſt, which this Tradition of Appeals from Churches, <hi>in re propriâ,</hi> to Superiour Eccleſiaſtical Judicatories, contradicteth, and ſo, maketh the Commandment of Chriſt void, and of none effect. It remaineth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that the Church of a particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation is the higheſt Tribunal under Chriſt, in ſuch things as are proper to it ſelf.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="corollary">
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:41503:77"/>
                  <head>3. <hi>Corollary.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Then intireneſs of Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in a particular Church compleated with its Officers, <hi>in re propriâ,</hi> will well conſiſt with that communion of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which the Scripture eſtabliſheth. The reaſon is, becauſe both are the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Chriſt, and Chriſts Ordinances do not interfere. As the Communion of Neighbour-Families doth not croſs the compleat Government of ſeveral Families within themſelves, reſpectively, in things properly Domeſtical. And as communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among Kingdoms and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, hindreth not the intireneſs of Juriſdiction in each Kingdom and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth within it ſelf, in its proper concernments; So it is in the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Churches. Therefore Church-communion muſt be only, in a way of Brotherly aſſociation, for mutual helpful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in matters of this nature, but not in way of ſubordination, or ſubjection of one Church to the Eccleſiaſtical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether of another Church, or of the Elders of ſeveral Churches aſſembled in Claſſes or Synods. The Communion of Churches, in the former way, is exerciſed according to Rule, in ſundry caſes, as
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:41503:77"/> 1. In mutual care. 2. In recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Members. 3. In participation of ſuch Ordinances as are for comfort and ſtrengthning the Members of other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches occaſionally. 4. In relieving and ſuccouring one another. 5. In counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing, by giving the right hand of fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip unto a Church in its firſt gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and unto Elders at their Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 6. In conſulting one with another, when we have occaſion to require the Judgment and Counſel of other Churches, concerning any Perſon or Cauſe,<note place="margin">See theſe particulars proved, in the Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form of Church-Diſcipline publiſhed-by the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod at <hi>Cambridge</hi> in <hi>New-England, Anno.</hi> 1649. the eighth moneth, <hi>Chap.</hi> 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they may be better acquainted than our ſelves. 7. In admoniſhing one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, in caſe of publick ſcandal. All theſe (and if withdrawing fellowſhip up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on juſt cauſes, be added to them) are no more than one Apoſtle may do to another, without exerciſing Church-Government over them. Communion of Churches in the latter way, of ſubordination or ſubjection to other Churches or Synods, <hi>in re propriâ,</hi> the Scripture no where approveth. Not of one Church to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for there is a parity among Churches, <hi>and par in parem non habet imperium.</hi> Nor of one Church to a Synod made up of the Elders of ſundry Neighbour-Churches. The Aſſembly in <hi>Act.</hi> 15. Is a pattern
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:41503:78"/> they ſay of ſuch a Synod. Let us ſee how their Claſſical Aſſemblies anſwer it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That was no ſet meeting, moneth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or quarterly, but meerly occaſional, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.1, 2.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If was not an Aſſembly of Elders meeting apart from the Brethren of the Church where they aſſembled, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 22, 23.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It was but a meeting of two Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that of <hi>Antioch</hi> ſending their Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, with <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and that at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Apoſtles (whoſe reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, for the preſent, was there) joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4, 6.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That aſſembly gave their judgment, both of the Doctrine taught at <hi>Antioch,</hi> &amp; of the perſons that taught it, as trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and ſubverters, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 24. but did nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Excommunicate them, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Church to Excommunicate them.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. They directed and charged the Church from the Word, what they ſhould do, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 28, 29. but they did not do their Acts of Power for them.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Nor did this Aſſembly exerciſe Church-government over that Church at <hi>Antioch,</hi> or any other Church or Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, in admiſſion of their Members, or
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:41503:78"/> in Ordination of their Officers, or in Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Seals, or in Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating, or in reverſing or nullifying the cenſure inflicted by the Church. For theſe were <hi>res propria</hi> to every particular Church within it ſelf. Yet, becauſe I ſtudy peace, and conſent with godly Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ſo far as it may ſtand with Truth, I willingly grant, that other Churches, and Synods rightly gathered and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, have ſo much Power and Authority, even in theſe matters, as I can find any warrant for in Scripture; being willing alſo to yield further if it can be cleared from Scripture, that more is due unto them. There are two Caſes, wherein the <hi>res propria</hi> of a particular Church, may fall under the cognizance and determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of other Churches or Synods.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. When they want ſufficient light, or competent conſent among themſelves, which was the caſe of the Church at <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och;</hi> provided, that they have liberty to chooſe ſuch a Church or Churches, for this purpoſe, as themſelves approve to be fitteſt for attainment of their end, in ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing light, as the Church at <hi>Antioch</hi> agreed to ſend to that at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> though two hundred miles diſtant from them. But, if they have ſufficient light within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:41503:79"/> and hold it forth convictingly from Scripture, the Elders and Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Members of the Church, and major part of the Brethren by far conſenting therein, no Rule requireth or alloweth, that, for the wilfulneſs of a Delinquent, who will not hear the Church, or of two or three Brethren, who ſide with him, and refuſe to joyn with the Church in cenſuring him, the Church ſhould be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from proceeding, till other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches or Elders have been conſulted. For if this be granted, 1. It will diſturb all Church-Proceedings. 2. And if it be brought to a Claſſis, it muſt iſſue there by the Vote of the major part, if as many Elders in that Aſſembly diſſent, as Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren did before in the Church-meeting, ſo that nothing is gained thereby. And if the Delinquent, for the ſame reaſon, appeal to a Synod, there may be the ſame iſſue, and ſo appeals may be drawn fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, till a Delinquent wreſt himſelf at laſt from all power of cenſure. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Caſe is, when that which is <hi>res pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pria,</hi> in the thing done, ſimply conſidered, becomes <hi>res communis</hi> in the Cauſe or ground of proceeding. For though re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of Members, Election, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Officers, and Adminiſtration of
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:41503:79"/> Seals and Cenſures, be Acts of the power given by Chriſt to particular Churches; yet it never was the mind of Chriſt, to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh, by that Grant, an abſolute power in ſuch Churches, to corrupt the Faith and Worſhip of God, in themſelves, and in other Churches. If therefore a Church, that was planted a noble <hi>Vine, wholly a a right Seed, ſhall turn into the degenerate Plants of a ſtrange Vine unto God,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Heretical, or Schiſmatical, or ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalouſly corrupt, and therefore receive into their fellowſhip known Hereticks, and Schiſmaticks, and chooſe ſuch into Office, and refuſe to admit into fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or Office, ſuch as are ſound in the Faith, becauſe they are ſound in the Faith and Order of the Goſpel, and caſt out from their fellowſhip ſuch as teſtifie, according to Rule, againſt theſe evils, and refuſe to conſent with them therein; &amp;c. the Neighbour Church, or Churches, or Elders, and Brethren Aſſembled in a Synod (if the evil ſpread to the diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, corrupting, or ſcandalizing of many Churches) have power, and it is their duty, 1. To conſider of this Matter, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.6. 2. To argue, debate, and determine according to the Word, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 7.-23. 3. To publiſh the ſame to
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:41503:80"/> the Church or Churches whom it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth, <hi>verſ.</hi> 23. to bear witneſs againſt their corruptions in Doctrine or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and to give directions from the Word, for the Reformation thereof, <hi>verſ.</hi> 24, 28, 29. 4. Such Determinations, and Directions being found conſonant to the Word of God in Scripture, the Church to whom they are ſent, are to receive them with due reverence and ſubmiſſion, as to the Ordinance of God. Or, 5. In caſe of obſtinate perſiſtance of ſuch a Church or Churches in their ſcandalous evils againſt light convictingly held forth, the Churches ſo offended, or ſcandalized by them, are to withdraw from them the right hand of fellowſhip and Church-Communion, till they repent and reform. This follows, in proportion, from the contrary, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.9. and <hi>à pari,</hi> 2 Theſ. 3.6, 14. there being a like reaſon of Churches and Perſons, in this reſpect. Yet ſuch offended Churches and Synods, are not to exerciſe Church-cenſures, in way of Diſcipline, nor any other Act of Church-Government, as neither did that Aſſembly, in <hi>Act.</hi> 15.29.</p>
                  <p>Here I ſhall crave leave to joyn with my Brethren in adding ſome caution touching the Communion and Conſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:41503:80"/> of Churches, <q>To ſee that this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociation of Churches be not perverted,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> of the Keys, <hi>p.</hi> 57.</note> either to the oppreſſion, or diminution of the juſt Liberty and Authority of each particular Church within it ſelf, who being well ſupplyed with a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and expert <hi>Presbytery</hi> of their own, do walk in their integrity, according to the Truth and Peace of the Goſpel. Let Synods have their juſt Authority in all Churches, how pure ſoever, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining ſuch <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, as are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite for the edification of all Churches, acording to God: but in the Election and Ordination of Officers, and cenſure of offenders, let it ſuffice the Churches Conſociate to aſſiſt one another with their Counſel, and right hand of fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, when they ſee a particular Church to uſe their Liberty and Power aright. But let them not put forth the Power of their Community, either to take ſuch Church Acts out of their hands, or to hinder them in their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful courſe, unleſs they ſee them thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> ignorance or weakneſs, to abuſe their Liberty and Authority in the Goſpel. All the Liberties of the Churches were purchaſed to them by the precious Blood of the Lord Jeſus, and therefore may
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:41503:81"/> not the Churches give them away, nor many Churches take them out of the hands of one.<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard</hi>'s &amp; Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s Defenſe of the 9 Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in anſw. to Mr. <hi>Ball.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Others expreſs their apprehenſions, in way of Caution, touching this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, thus.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Aſſociation of divers particular Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, we hold needful, as well as the combination of Members into one Church; yet ſo, as there be no Schiſm of one from another, nor uſurpation of one over another; that either one ſhould deprive the reſt of peace, by Schiſm, or many ſhould deprive any one of its power by uſurpation. Hence a Fraternal Conſociation we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. <hi>Conſociation;</hi> for mutual Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and help, to prevent, or remove, Sin, or Schiſm: Yet <hi>Fraternal only,</hi> to to preſerve each others Power. Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation of Churches we would have <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulativè</hi> (not in words, but in deed) to ſtrengthen the power of particular Churches: Not <hi>privativè,</hi> to take away any power, which they had from the gift of Chriſt before. For, as on the one ſide, it may ſeem ſtrange, that one Church offending ſhould have no means of Cure by the <hi>conceived power</hi> of many; ſo, on the other ſide, the danger may
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:41503:81"/> appear as great, and frequently falls out, that, when many Churches are ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, one innocent Church may be hurt by the Uſurpation of all. And hence we ſee not, but that Fraternal Conſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the beſt Medicine to heal the Wounds of both.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hereunto I ſhall add, that, as theſe god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Learned Brethren ſpeak nothing for the Claſſical Power of Elders, for which the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> contend, <hi>tanquam pro aris &amp; focis;</hi> ſo in that Communion of Churches, which I with them look at as the Ordinance of Chriſt, due moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt be exerciſed by Neighbour Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that their exerciſing brotherly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in teſtifying againſt ſuch Acts in a particular Church, as they conceive to be aberrations from the Rule, be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Scripture-Light, with Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility; and that,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Held forth by them, they looking at themſelves, though as Elders, yet not as Apoſtles, nor as infallibly aſſiſted, or carried by the Spirit, above all poſſibility of erring, in their Determinations and Counſels, and therefore do not in a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterly way impoſe their Determinations and Counſels upon others, but propound them in the fear of God, to be examined
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:41503:82"/> by the Scripture, and received only ſo far, as they ſhall be found to agree there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. And, if that Church hold forth Reaſons of their contrary apprehenſions, let them be duly weighed, and anſwered convictingly; or let that Church be left at liberty, to walk according to their own light, <hi>in re propriâ,</hi> without offenſe, or diſturbance.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Godly Wiſdom is to be exerciſed in ſuch proceedings, in making difference between Cauſe and Cauſe; which will not ſuffer Churches to connive at groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſcandals, nor to withdraw the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand of fellowſhip from any Church up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſmall differences in Judgement or Practice, much leſs, for Cenſuring, and holding under Cenſure impenitent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, when the ſcandalous obſtinacy of delinquents is <hi>res propriâ</hi> to that Church, though ſome other Churches (being miſ-led by their Guides, who poſſibly may ſide, more than they ought, with the delinquent, out of ſome ſecret grutch againſt the Elders of that Church) declare it to be their Judgment, that the party ſhould not have been layed under that Cenſure, or ſhould now be releaſed from it. To withdraw the right-hand of fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip from a Church for ſuch a cauſe,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:41503:82"/> is contrary to Rules of true Wiſdom. If a Church be found in the Faith and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Goſpel, greater matters than this will cauſe no breach of Communion between Churches, where brotherly Communion is exerciſed with true Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and godly Wiſdom. See the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of that <hi>Affrican</hi> Synod, whereof <hi>Cyprian</hi> wrote thus to <hi>Stephanus. Caete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſcimus quoſdam, quod ſemel imbiberint,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cypr. l. <hi>2.</hi> Ep. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>nolle deponere, nec propoſitum ſuum facilè mutare, ſed ſalvo inter collegas pacis &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiae vinculo, quaedam propria, quae apud ſe ſemel ſint uſurpata, retinere. Quâ in re, nec nos cuiquam facimus aut legem damus, cum habeat in Eccleſiae adminiſtratione vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatis ſuae arbitrium liberum unuſquiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> praepoſitus, rationem actus ſui Domino red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diturus.</hi> Yet theſe proper practices of ſome Churches, differed from the Decree of that Synod, which was eſtabliſhed, as he ſaith, <hi>Conſenſu &amp; authoritate commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni.</hi> Nor will there ever be end of brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches among Churches, unleſs due mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, in ſuch Caſes, be exerciſed, that love among Churches may be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Unto theſe let it be added, that as the Foundation of the Communion of Churches is <hi>brotherly love,</hi> ſo all the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:41503:83"/> Churches ſhould ſhew to any one Church, and before other Churches, the proof of their love, in not eaſily receiving ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt the proceedings of it, though from ſome Elder or Paſtor, or Teacher of another Church, who may poſſibly ſpeak againſt them out of envy, or ill will; much more, in not countenancing a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured Delinquent, complaining againſt the Church and Elders, by whom he was cenſured, in a diſorderly tumultuous manner, as deſirous to beget reproach and trouble to that Church, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions and Diviſions among the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Elders,<note place="margin">Cyprian. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Ep. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> from an evil ſpirit of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge. The <hi>Affrican</hi> Paſtors were care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful hereof, as <hi>Cyprian</hi> notes. <hi>Cum ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſit omnibus nobis, &amp; aequum ſit pariter ac juſtum, ut uniuſcujuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> cauſa illic audia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ubi eſt crimen admiſſum, &amp; ſingulis paſtoribus portio egregis ſit aſcripta; quam regat unuſquiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> &amp; gubernet, rationem ſui actus Domino rediturus, oportet uti<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> eos quibus praeſumus, non circumcurdare, nec Epiſcoporum concordiam cohaerentem ſuâ ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolâ &amp; fallaci temeritate, collidere, ſed agere illic cauſam ſuam, ubi, &amp; accuſatores habere, &amp; teſtes ſui criminis, poſſint.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, If the Elders and Meſſengers of Churches aſſembled in a Synod, ſhall
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:41503:83"/> determine any thing contrary to the Rule, and prejudicial to the intireneſs of the Churches Power, within it ſelf, the Church may, and ought, to refuſe ſuch Sanctions, as not being ſancited by the Lord. The Communion of Churches being rightly ordered, according to what hath been ſaid, is a ſufficient Spiritual Remedy againſt all thoſe inconveniences, which ſome think cannot be redreſſed, unleſs Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction over par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches be eſtabliſhed in Claſſes and Synods: As, if a Church fall into two Factions &amp; Oppoſitions within it ſelf, or, if there be ſcandalous contention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two Churches, or between the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhip and Brother-hood of the ſame Church; or, if a whole Church be under ſcandalous Delinquencies: I ſay, theſe and the like inconveniencies will be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter redreſſed, in this way, than in that of Claſſical Government. For, this way is grounded upon Divine Inſtitution, ſo is not that: And the bleſſing of Chriſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows and accompanies his own Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, not mens devices. If <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> put forth his hand to ſtay the Ark, his good intention could not juſtifie his action, but his not acting according to Gods order was his death. The Prelates had as plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:41503:84"/> a plea for their Juriſdiction over Churches, and taking the Keyes out of their hands, <hi>viz.</hi> for Unity, Peace, and Conformity; yet the vanity of it is now manifeſted unto all men. Laſtly, The ſame inconveniences may befall Claſſical and Synodal Aſſemblies, yea, and Oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menical Councils, and what remedy is there for them? Not ſo much, as this way of Communion of Churches afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to particular Churches.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="corollary">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Corollary</hi> 4.</head>
                  <p>Then intireneſs of Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in a particular Congregation, <hi>in re propriâ,</hi> ought to be thankfully received, rightly improved, and faithfully preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, without violation of it, both by the Members of particular Churches, and by other Churches, and their Officers.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It muſt be thankfully received, as a bleſſing promiſed of God unto his people, <hi>whoſe hearts are ingaged to approach unto him,</hi> Jer. 30.21. The grant by Charter, of intireneſs of Government within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, unto Cities and Corporations, hath ever been highly eſteemed, as an Act of ſpecial grace from the Soveraign Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. It was for the injoyment of this Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, with the conſequents of it, that the <hi>chief Captain,</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> 22.25,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:41503:84"/> 26, 28. <hi>purchaſed his freedom in Rome</hi> with a great ſumme of money. This grant to particular Churches is advantagious to the Members of them, ſundry wayes. 1. For their eaſe, in having their Cauſes heard, examined and iſſued, at home, without chargeable, tireſome journeys to the Claſſical or Synodal Aſſembly, to have their matters determined there. 2. For incouragement and liberty of the ſpirit and ſpeech of him that is to anſwer before his Brethen and the Elders, who have a Member-like and Paſtoral care and reſpect of him, whereas the preſence of ſundry ſtrange faces of perſons of ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Rank and Quality, would not a little daunt him, which might occaſion his falling in his Cauſe. 3. For their ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction concerning the Churches proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, where, as all circumſtances can be beſt cleared, ſo more moderation may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally be expected from their own Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Brethren, than from ſtrangers, comparatively, and from ſuch as are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the ſame cenſures, and the ſame either hath been, or may be, their own caſe, they know not how ſoon, (which are ſtrong inducements to moderation, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.9. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1.) than from a Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory of conſtant Judges, who think
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:41503:85"/> themſelves out of that danger. 4. For common edification in the Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal way, all may hear and be edified by their preſence in Church-proceedings, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.11. This they looſe, in the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterial</hi> way, Claſſicall Aſſemblies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting only of Elders meeting and acting apart.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It muſt be rightly improved, which is then done, when Church-proceedings are orderly carried according to Chriſts Rules, both by the Elderſhip and Frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, acting the Power which Chriſt hath delegated to them, reſpectively, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their ſeveral intereſts, in the due order, and with mutual conſent, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It muſt be faithfully preſerved without violation. 1. By the Members of particular Churches, ſubmitting to the Ordinance of Chriſt, whereby the Church, acting according to Rule, is made under Chriſt, the higheſt Eccleſiaſtical Tribunal, in its own matters, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. without ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing to other Eccleſiaſtical Judicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, who have no power from Chriſt to diſpenſe Church-cenſures, or to releaſe men from them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.18.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> What if the Brother be not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in the equity of the Churches pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding?
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:41503:85"/> 
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Elders having declared the mind of Chriſt from Scripture to guide their proceedings, and the Brethren ether <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or the major part, by far, judging accordingly, let him ſuſpect his own apprehenſions, fearing that Satans temptations, and his own corruptions, Pride, and ſelf-flattery may darken and harden him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.14. 2. Let him attend ſeriouſly to the light held forth from Scripture, for his conviction, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. praying the Lord to make it effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al in him. 3. Let him thankfully cloſe with the light that doth ſhine unto him, and anſwerably judge and condemn in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the evil, which that light reproveth, and follow on to know the whole mind of Chriſt concerning the nature and compaſs of his guilt, ſeeking unto the Elders for further help, with a ſelf-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirit, that he may come up fully to the Rule. 4. If he cannot ſhew convict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly to the Church ſome errours in the Elders expounding or applying the Rule to the Caſe, whereupon the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure proceeded, let him fall under the Rule, or look at it as his great ſin, and violation of his Covenant, which bound him to ſubmit unto the judgement of the Church, if he finde that, through
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:41503:86"/> ſinful prejudice, he cannot receive the light held forth, when he hath no obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of weight againſt it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Other Churches and the Elders of them ought to preſerve the intireneſs of Power of every particular Church, <hi>in re propriâ,</hi> inviolate. The Law of Love and Righteouſneſs binds every man here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. One Corporation muſt uphold the juſt Rights, Liberties, and Power of another. <hi>If a man ſee his brothers Ox or Sheep go aſtray, he muſt in any caſe bring them again unto his brother,</hi> Deut. 22.1. much more if he ſee a Sheep of Chriſt go aſtray by ſinful prejudice againſt the Church, he muſt in any caſe convince him of his errour, and bring him again to the Church, as the Angel returned <hi>Hagar</hi> to <hi>Sarah</hi> her Miſtreſs, <hi>Gen.</hi> 16.8, 9. For this purpoſe, 1. They muſt <hi>not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive an accuſation againſt an Elder</hi> (much leſs, againſt the Church and Elderſhip) <hi>under two or three witneſſes,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.19. therefore much leſs, from a Delinquent under publick cenſure, and that in his one cauſe. 2. If more joyn with him atteſting what he ſaith; they muſt ſee, 1 Whether they do it, in a way of facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſiding with a cenſured Delinquent againſt the Church, or no. If yea; they
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:41503:86"/> muſt teſtifie againſt their way, as contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Rule, and avoid them, as diſturbers of the peace of the Church, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. If not; they muſt inquire, 1, whether they have pleaded with the Church it ſelf, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.2. in ſuch manner as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh ſuch as would approve themſelves to love the Truth and Peace, <hi>Zach.</hi> 8.21. before they become accuſers of the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren unto others. 2 Whether they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed peaceably, or tumultuouſly? and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuoſly they do act, if they ſeek nor Light in the uſe of Means, firſt, at home, but refuſe help that way, when it is offered them, that they may make trouble and diſturbance to the Church, by ſpreading their complaints abroad, and thoſe, not to ſome one Church, without whoſe help the queſtion cannot be ended, as the Church at <hi>Antioch</hi> ſent to the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but to eight or nine Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ſome nearer, ſome far diſtant from the Church, ſome 40, 50, 100, 150 miles off, and that without giving notice of their purpoſe to the Church, or having their conſent thereunto, or ſo much as to the ſtating of the queſtion. If ſo, they may clearly ſee an evil ſpirit working in the buſineſs, with which, others ſhould have no fellowſhip, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.20. 3 Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:41503:87"/> they do poſitively juſtifie the Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in that, for which he was cenſured, and upon what grounds; or only declare their good Opinion of the Delinquent in ſome reſpects, and that they are not clear concerning the equity of the cenſure. If the latter, it is the duty of thoſe to whom they thus ſpeak, to convince them of the error of their way. 4 Whether they come only in a back-biting way, or are willing to ſpeak the ſame things publickly before the Church, which they accuſe privately. If not, they muſt be convinced of their ſinning againſt common equity, <hi>Act.</hi> 25.16. 5 What the end is which they propound unto themſelves in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this courſe? whether it be for light only? or, for the nullifying of the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure by the power of others? If the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; they cannot ſafely conclude any thing, <hi>alterâ parte inauditâ,</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.17. If the latter, they muſt profeſs, that they have no ſuch Power, but all that they can do, is, to inform themſelves from the Church, whether their report be true, or not, and to give ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe from Scripture, as the caſe requires, according to their judgement, exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in the mean ſpace, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:41503:87"/> the Rule in Memberlike ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Power of their Church, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> But ſuppoſe that the party cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured think he can prove that he is wronged; is there no courſe to be taken for the freeing of him from a ſentence that is unjuſt in his apprehenſion?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> If he hath held forth convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing light (as he conceiveth) to the Church, to prove that he is wronged, and hath waited patiently for redreſs, but can find none, and therefore deſireth to joyn with ſome other Church; he may remove his dwelling, if no other Church be in the ſame place, or, without that, if there be, and he may offer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to their fellowſhip, making known to them his caſe. If, in other reſpects, they approve him, as one, whoſe fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with them would be helpful, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to them; they will acquaint the Church, whence he came, with his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and crave their advice, which will draw from that Church a full Narrative of his Caſe: Upon examination whereof theſe, who deſire his fellowſhip, will labour with him, to further his repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and his holding it forth to the
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:41503:88"/> ſatisfaction of that offended Church, according to Rule; which being done, the Church that was offended will be reconciled to him, and forgive him, and confirm their love to him, in the Lord, and recommend him to that fellowſhip where he deſires to ſettle. But, if they will not; the Church that hath thus far laboured in the buſineſs, will acquaint other neighbour-Churches with the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and crave their advice, who find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, either that the Church did err in judgement, or that the Delinquent hath ſatisfied the Rule of Repentance, will ſignifie their apprehenſions to both the Churches, and accordingly the party is, either releaſed by the one, or received by the other, each of them preſerving its Church-power in <hi>re propriâ,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their light, maintaining ſtill Church-Communion, notwithſtanding their different apprehenſions touching this matter.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If the caſe be reducible to what is noted in the third <hi>Corollary,</hi> there you may find a ſufficient Remedy preſcribed, according to Congregational Principles, without his remove.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In ſome Caſes, a miſchief is to be
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:41503:88"/> choſen, before an inconvenience, as Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers ſpeak. Better it is that the Church want a Remedy for a Caſe that may not happen in a mans life, than to be under the continual droppings of Claſſical Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction over them in all Caſes.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. We have formerly proved, that Claſſical Juriſdiction is ſo far from being helpful to Churches, that it fruſtrates Chriſts grant of Power to particular Churches in <hi>re propriâ.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
